中文字幕+时间轴: EzDone Studio & MarcusZ
Subtitle & Timeline: EzDone Studio & MarcusZ
乔布斯传
jOBS
苹果公司议事厅
员工大会, 2001年
我很开心来到这里.
I'm really excited to be here.
今天, 我们将给大家展示一个非常特殊的产品.
We have something really special to share with you today.
在今年, iMac和Powerbook加起来,
In total, between iMac and PowerBook lines,
我们一共卖掉300多万台.
we have sold over three million units this year.
行, 就这样了.
Okay. That's it.
对了, 还有一件事.
Well, maybe there's one more thing.
我要给大家展示一件令人惊奇的产品.
I'm about to show you something that's amazing.
一件前所未有, 闻所未闻的产品.
Something that no one else in the world has seen yet.
现在, 强尼, 我, 还有一小组人
Now, Jony, myself and a small team
我们非常辛苦为这个秘密的项目工作着.
have been working really hard on a secret project,
大家也知道我在忙这个项目,
which is something I've been known to do
一直在忙于此.
from time to time.
我马上要介绍的这款产品
The device I'm about to introduce to you
将改变整个产业.
is gonna revolutionize an entire industry.
它是一款音乐播放设备.
It's a music playing device.
好吧.
Okay.
我们一会儿再谈细节.
We'll get to that in a minute.
因为我想先说, 它所代表的意义和它的实际用途同样的伟大.
Because what it represents is as important as what it is.
这是一个能触动心灵的工具.
It's a tool for the heart.
当某样东西能触碰一个人心灵的时候,
And when you can touch someone's heart,
它就变得意义非凡.
that's limitless.
我自卖自夸一下, 这东西酷毙了.
If I do say so myself, it's insanely cool.
它是一款音乐播放器.
It's a music player.
也就是在你口袋里装下一千首歌.
It's a thousand songs in your pocket.
我将给你们介绍:
I'd like to introduce you
...iPod
to the iPod.
嘿, 乔布斯.
Hey, Jobs.
起床了, 哥们, 醒醒.
Get up, man. Wake up.
我醒着.
I'm up.
我醒着呢.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
- 嗨, 丹尼尔.  - 嘿, 忙什么呢?
- Hey, Daniel. - Hey, what's going on?
- 你在读那本"活在当下"的书吧?  - 是啊, 那本书很棒.
- Are you reading Be Here Now? - Yeah, it's amazing.
我正在读, 很好看.
I'm reading that right now. It's unbelievable.
它是一本更高层面的书. 嗯, 既然我们碰上了,
It's the next level. Hey, speaking of Be Here,
跟我说说昨天晚上干什么了? 你去哪儿了?
what happened to you last night? Where'd you go?
我得上课去了. 我知道, 我知道.
I had to study. I know, I know.
你知道的, 我不是宣讲"读书无用论",
You know, I'm not dismissing the value of higher education,
但是上大学是以丧失实际工作经验为代价的.
I'm just saying it comes at the expense of experience.
系统化教学的产物就是系统的一部分...
The system can only produce the system.
我可不想变成一个死板的书呆子, 你也应该如此.
I don't want to be a part of that. Neither should you.
我同意你. 不过人要有足够胆量才能像你一样休学.
I agree with you. It takes balls to drop out like you did.
这就是为什么你也应该休学.
That's why you should.
- 我可不行. 我是说... - 史蒂文.
- I can't. I mean that... - Steven.
能借过跟你聊两句吗?
Might I borrow you for a moment?
- 打断你们了, 再见.  - 一定的.
- I'll see you in, see you later. - Sure.
- 谢谢.  - 我希望我没有打断你们的谈兴正浓.
- Thank you. - So I hope I'm not interrupting.
你的课程上得怎么样?
What about your classes?
我不再是学生了, 杰克.
I'm not a student anymore, Jack.
呃, 你在这里(旁听), 学习.
Well, you're here, and you're learning.
于我而言, 你跟学生没什么分别.
Sure sounds like a student to me.
如果你想赶我走...
If you want me gone...
我为什么要赶你走啊, 史蒂夫?
Why would I want you gone, Steven?
我很高兴你愿意待在这里.
I'm glad that you're here.
付不付学费都没关系.
Whether you're paying or not.
现在, 你经常拿个本子闲晃,
Now, you're always carrying this notebook around.
貌似你自诩是个艺术家吧.
You obviously fancy yourself as an artist.
为什么不去上个设计类的课程呢?
Why don't you sit in on some design classes?
不. 呃, 我喜欢艺术之美, 但是仅限于言之有物的那种艺术.
No. Well, I like the idea of art, the beauty. But only in the right context.
但是我并不想以此为职业生涯. 我没有那种天分.
Just not as a career. I don't have the necessary talents.
但你不是对电子设备感兴趣吗? 工程类课程如何?
But aren't you interested in electronics? What about engineering?
合格的工程师的就业前景看涨. 你看这主意怎么样?
There's a growing market for qualified technicians. What about that?
我不想花我父母的钱
I don't want to spend my parents' money
去读取一个学位了事, 而且不想成为...
to get a degree and become something
这么容易被人淡忘的电气工程师.
as forgettable as an electrician.
等会儿, 什么, 读取一个学位是虚度光阴? 因此...
Excuse me, what, a degree is a waste of time now? So...
对某些人而言是的. 对另外一些人而言, 它是很有效的证明. 工作保证.
For some. For others it offers validation. Job security.
- 史蒂夫... - 拜拜.
- Steve... - I'll see you around.
史蒂文.
Steven.
那下次再聊.
To be continued.
你在干什么?
What are you working on?
没什么, 书法课的家庭作业而已.
Nothing, really. It's homework for calligraphy class.
很漂亮啊.
It's beautiful.
是的, 这门课的老师是一位僧侣.
Yeah, the teacher's this monk, or something.
僧侣?
A monk?
是, 他叫罗伯特.帕拉迪诺.
Yeah. Robert Palladino.
他的课非常有启发性.
He's totally inspiring.
对了, 我叫茱莉.
My name's Julie.
你要走啊?
Are you leaving?
是啊. 我得走了.
Yeah. I have to go.
来点吗?
You want a hit?
好的.
Yes.
好的, 来一点.
Yes, I do.
我能多拿点吗?
Can I take a couple?
- 当然.  - 给我朋友.
- Sure. - For my friends.
呃, 我朋友...还有我女朋友.
Well, my friend, and my girlfriend.
好美.
It's so beautiful.
好像一扇通往整个世界的窗户.
Like a window to the world.
你觉得太空是什么样子?
What do you think it's like in space?
一定...
It's...
美到无以言表.
beyond understanding.
是的.
Yeah.
谁会做那种事: 生了一个孩子,
Who has a baby,
...之后, 就那样无情地抛弃掉?
and then just throws it away like it's nothing?
你又在想你亲生父母的事?
You talking about your birth parents?
哦, 别说了, 别说了.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no.
好伤感. 真的, 太令我伤感了. 我...
That's bad. Yeah. That's making me really sad. I...
不好意思, 我的过去让你High不起来了.
Sorry that my life is ruining your high.
没关系.
It's okay.
当你不在的时候, 我会想你的.
I miss you when you're not around.
我爱你, 史蒂夫.
I love you, Steve.
我爱你.
I love you.
宇宙啊, 无边无垠的黑暗王国.
Space. The endless black deep.
到底过去的哲人告诉了我们什么?
What was it that that guru used to tell us?
别蹉跎岁月.
There is no time to waste.
你听见了吗?
Do you hear that?
什么?
What?
他又去了远方.
There he goes again.
书法是一种把艺术和视觉结合的表现形式.
Calligraphy is the artful and visual expression of communication.
比如说Garamond字体
Take Garamond, for example.
特殊的字体设计是为了让每一种阅读体验
A typeface specifically designed to make the very act of reading
更加的自然.
more natural.
电脑之所以被发明, 是为了让人们的生活更容易.
Computers are inherently designed to make your lives easier.
理论上讲, 没有什么是电脑做不到的.
Theoretically there's no limit to what computers can do.
你出生时是谁, 并不重要；
It is not who you were at birth that matters
重要的是, 你在有生之年做了什么.
but what you do with the time you are given.
人生苦短,
The moment of your death is fixed.
在生命的终点, 一切将归于平静.
Life is but a journey to serenity, to its completion.
简单地做好自己.
Be as simple as you can be.
你会惊奇地发现生活变得简单
You'll be astonished to see how uncomplicated
而且快乐.
and happy your life can become.
我不知道我回家了要做什么.
I don't even know what I'm gonna do when I go back home.
你呢?
What about you?
回到矽谷后你想做什么?
What are you gonna do when you get back to The Valley?
史蒂夫?
Steve?
史蒂夫? 你还好吗?
Steve? You okay?
不, 不, 不! 这还是黑白两色的.
No. No, no! No. It's still black and white.
老百姓想要彩色的.
People want color.
- 这产品过去一直没有彩色的.  - 那么?
- Pong didn't have color. - So?
让我们把产品做得更好一点点.
Let's do something better.
这东西没办法做成彩色的.
It can't do color.
谁说的?
Says who?
好. 你不愿意做任何努力.
Okay, you refuse to do anything
稍微困难一点的事情你就放弃.
that vaguely escapes your comfort zone.
你又不是我老板.
You're not even my boss.
呃, 我觉得我应该做你的老板.
Well, I damn sure should be.
嘿, 乔布斯!
Hey. Jobs!
你在干嘛呢, 史蒂夫?
What're you doing, Steve?
他就是个蠢货.
He's an idiot.
你们知道的, 这屋子里一半的人
You know, and half the people around here
根本不懂设计产品.
don't know how to design shit.
大家对你的行为很不满.
People are complaining about your behavior.
- 怎么啦? 没错. - 有关我的?
- Okay? And, yeah. - About mine?
还有你身上的味道.
And your odor.
我要你去洗澡, 你洗了吗?
Are you showering like we discussed?
你要我不要打赤脚, 我已经照做了.
I'm wearing shoes. You asked me
我确实穿上鞋子了.
to wear shoes, and I've got them on.
这不是问题的关键所在, 史蒂夫.
That's not part of the deal, Steve.
你得学会跟别人共事.
You've gotta learn how to work well with other people.
我只是想把事情做得好一些.
I'm just trying to do it right, Al.
我知道.
I know you are.
那就别管我.
Then let me.
听着, 史蒂夫!
Listen, Steve!
你很棒, 非常棒!
You're good. You're damn good.
但你就是个浑球.
But you're an asshole.
呃, 天哪...
Well, that...
嘿, 让我说完.
Hey. Let me finish.
我想让你待在这里, 我真心这样想.
I want you here. I really do.
但你必须改变自己.
Something's gotta change.
- 让我独自做一个项目.  - 什么?
- Give me my own project. - What?
把我自己的项目交给我做.
Give me my own project.
我独自一人完成.
I'll do it on my own.
我会做一个你从没见过的好游戏.
And I'll make the best damn game you have ever seen.
你说真的.
You're serious.
好吧, 史蒂夫.
Okay, Steve.
我需要有人重新制作一些有问题的游戏.
I need someone to reprogram a troublesome game.
但是我时间上很紧张.
But I'm on a tight deadline.
如果你能如期完工,
So if you can deliver,
我会付给你5,000美元.
we'll pay you up to $5,000.
- 5,000美元?  - 呣...
- $5,000? - Mmm-hmm.
好的.
Okay.
至于你的个人问题, 我有办法能解决.
And as for your personal issues, I think I may have a solution.
这有很多电路板.
It's so many circuits.
沃兹? 嘿, 我是史蒂夫.
Woz? Hey, it's Steve.
谢谢你帮忙.
Thanks for saving my ass.
没事, 我们是朋友. 这正是好朋友应该做的.
Of course. We're friends. That's, that's what friends do.
我实在没办法给别人打工.
I just can't work for other people.
我需要独立行动, 如果这事儿合理的话.
I guess I need my independence. If that makes any sense.
呃-哈.
Uh-huh.
我觉得非常合理.
That makes perfect sense.
不好意思, 大好的周末夜被我毁了.
I'm sorry for ruining your Friday night.
你在开玩笑吧? 这事儿很棒.
Are you kidding me? This is great.
我喜欢免费做这件事, 真的.
I'd do this for free. I really would.
但是, 好奇的是, 这个项目我们能拿多少钱?
But just out of curiosity, how much are we getting paid?
700美元.
$700.
好多啊.
Some big bucks there.
靠.
Shit.
真不错. 非常好.
This is good. Really good.
我知道.
I know.
喔, 4天就搞定, 你真不是盖的.
Wow. Four days. You aren't kidding around.
我还得给诺兰看一眼, 不过这真的很不错.
I'll have to show it to Nolan, but this is, this is good.
沃兹?
Woz?
嗨. 嗨.
Hi. Hi.
沃兹!
Woz!
嗨! 是的, 我在客厅里.
Hi! Yeah, I'm in the living room.
嘿. 好消息.
Hey. Good news.
呃? 我猜你老板喜欢那个游戏.
Huh? Let me guess, your bosses liked the video game.
- 他们确实喜欢!  - 哦.
- They loved it! - Ooh.
350美元! 唉哟, 不错的买卖哦.
$350. Whew! That's not bad.
不只是不错, 简直是超屌.
Not bad? It's great.
你在忙什么呢?
What are you working on?
我在给"对话式笑话机器"写笑话.
I'm writing jokes for my dial-a-joke machine.
我写出了不少绝对好笑的波兰笑话, 因为我是波兰人.
I've got some really good funny Polish jokes, which work because I'm Polish.
出去走走, 听听这段, 你觉得怎么样?
Hang out and tell me what you think of this one.
准备好了吗?
Ready? Ready?
新婚之夜, 波兰新娘会得到什么"长而硬"的东东?
What is long, and hard, that a Polish bride gets on her wedding night?
一个新的姓氏(从夫姓).
A new last name.
蛮好笑的.
That's hilarious.
不错吧, 对不对?
Pretty good, isn't it?
如果你遇见一个漂亮的波兰女孩, 你会叫她什么? 幸运妹.
What do you call a beautiful Polish girl? Lucky.
那是什么?
What's that?
呣?
Hmm?
哦.
Oh.
这个可厉害了.
That. Now that is gonna be cool.
这是个我正在研发的"个人电脑终端主板".
It's a computer terminal board I'm working on.
可以直接连上电视.
Hooks up to the TV for the display.
看起来像什么, 一个盒子? 你什么意思啊?
What is it like, a kit? What do you mean?
呃, 呃...
Well, well...
代码还有些毛病.
The code is still buggy,
理论上, 这能在荧幕上即时显示你的操作. 例如...
but in theory it'll display whatever you're working on. Like...
弄来看看.
Show me.
- 给你展示一下. - 行.
- Show you. - Okay.
哦!
Wow.
不管惠普公司喜不喜欢, 它意义重大.
I don't care if HP didn't like it. It matters.
对, 这东西很有潜力
Yeah. It's got potential.
不, 性手枪乐队那才叫有潜力. 这是历史的车轮.
No, the Sex Pistols have potential. This is the wheel.
它将推动新的产业革命.
It's the Industrial Revolution.
不再有平台, 不再有大型主机.
No more decks, no more mainframes.
它将改变一切.
That changes everything.
好吧, 挺酷的.
It's pretty cool, I guess.
- 嘿, 查理, 你好.  - 嘿.
- Hi, Charlene. Hello. - Hey.
太酷了, 而且很高深莫测. 你怎么不早告诉我?
Cool. It's profound. How could you not tell me about this before?
我不知道. 我就是自己玩玩, 我自己的个人爱好而已.
I don't know. I was just working on it for my own. It was a hobby.
没错, 你自己的个人爱好, 你喜欢.
Exactly. Exactly. For your own. For you.
这就是你想要的, 你真心会喜欢上的东西.
It's what you wanted. It's what your gut, your instinct wanted.
你的充满创意的脑袋想要一个不存在的东西.
Your big evolved brain wanted something that didn't exist,
你就把它做出来了.
so you just willed it into existence.
你叫它什么来着?
It's, what do you call the system?
操作系统?
The operating system?
- 操作系统, 刚给你演示过的... - 我就是这么称呼它的.
- The operating, and it just shows you... - That's what I call it.
是的, 就是一个能把用户操作即时显示出来的系统.
Yeah, it's just a real time display of current operations.
你在干什么, 你就能看见什么.
You can see what you're working on while you're working on it.
好. 听着...
Okay. Look...
你不明白这点吗? 这是自由.
Don't you get this? This is freedom.
自由的创作, 执行.
This is freedom to create, and to do, and to build,
- 像艺术家一样, 很个性化的.  - 瞧瞧, 瞧瞧.
- as artists, as individuals. - Look, look, look.
但是你看, 你想太多了.
But look, you're overreacting.
就算免费把这个操作系统开发出来, 我很怀疑你不会免费发放它,
Even if you were developing this for freaks like us, and I doubt you are,
没有人会因此想买一台电脑回家的. 没有人.
nobody wants to buy a computer. Nobody.
一个人从没见过某样东西时, 他怎么知道自己不想要它?
How does somebody know what they want if they've never even seen it?
呃?
Huh?
我们要去Home Brew电脑俱乐部
We're going to Homebrew.
靠, 绝对不去.
No... abs...
我不会在Home Brew做展示的.
I am not presenting anything at Homebrew.
坚决不要.
I'm... No.
这些人为毛开的这么慢? 闪开, 让路!
Why do people drive so slow? Get out! Move!
我现在告诉你, 我曾去过Home Brew俱乐部.
I'm telling you right now, I've been to Homebrew.
那些人口才不错.
I understand the caliber of people who speak there.
我可不是那样的人.
I'm not one of those people.
- 我跟你说这东西很好. - 我不是说...
- I'm telling you this thing is amazing. - I'm not...
你会很了不起的, 沃兹.
You're gonna be great, Woz.
史蒂夫, 请你帮个忙, 你能...
Steve, could you do me a favor, could you just please
开慢一点吗? 这样的话,
slow down a little bit so that I feel like
我还有机会活着到那里.
there's a chance we might actually get there alive.
我希望我们第一个到达, 第一个展示产品.
I want to get there first so we can present first.
你知道的, 如果我们要开公司,
You know if we're gonna do this thing,
我们得想个好名字.
we need to come up with a name.
是的, 我知道. 这名字得好记, 吸引人. 像...
Yeah, I know. Something catchy. Something...
我觉得名字里...
I've been thinking about it.
应该要有"电子".
...electric.
- 它得有点像... - 我不知道.
- It needs to feel like... - I don't know.
"企业号"计算机公司怎么样?
What about Enterprise Computers?
不.
No.
别给我来"星舰迷航"那套.
No Star Trek names.
- "柯克企业"怎么样?  - 我发誓...
- What about Kirk Enterprises? - I swear.
- 我要开车撞树了. - 好吧, 好吧.
- I will drive this car right off this road. - Fine, fine, fine, fine, fine!
- 我真的会撞上去哦. - 喔, 天啊! 冷静, 严肃一点.
- I will run the car right off the road. - Jesus! Calm down! Seriously.
好. 不要"星舰迷航"那种, 上帝啊.
Okay. Nothing Trekkie. Jesus.
它需要像...与人相关的东西, 你知道的?
It just needs to be, like, something that people will relate to, you know?
一些常见又好记的,
Like, it needs to be something that you see,
而且是人们喜欢的 -- "哥们, 我想拥有它. "
and you're just, like, "Man, I just gotta have it."
Apple.
你说什么?
Excuse me?
- Apple?  水果那个Apple?
- Apple. - Apple, like the fruit?
代表着万物之源的水果 -- Apple. 大道至简, 却又博大精深.
The fruit of creation. Apple. It's simple but sophisticated.
而且, 在电话簿上排名也比Atari公司靠前.
It comes before Atari in the phone book, too.
这比我想的"向量光电脑公司"好多了.
That is so much better than Phaser Beam Computers.
它得名于一种水果.
It's naming it after a fruit.
苹果. 苹果电脑公司.
Apple. Apple Computer.
还有个唱片公司也叫Apple?
But, what about Apple Records?
- Apple唱片?  - 嗯, 披头士创立的公司, 傻X...
- Apple Records? - The Beatles' label, stu...
什么? 披头士拥有"苹果"商标?
What, they own the word "apple"?
你为什么总是讨厌披头士?
Why do you always hate The Beatles?
呃, 我并不是讨厌披头士.
Well, I do not hate The Beatles.
-不, 你就是讨厌, 你总是讨厌... - 我不讨厌披头士.
- Yes, you do. You always... - I do not hate The Beatles.
他们..., 不是迪伦.鲍勃(美国20世纪60年代城市民谣领军人物), 你知道的.
They're just, they're not Dylan, and you know that.
行了, 你总是做这样的比较.
Okay, and that's a comparison that you always make.
呃, 我... 就是因为这个比较显而易见.
Well, I... 'Cause it's obvious.
而且我不认为这很公平.
And I don't think it's fair.
Apple, 决定了? 就是Apple了?
Apple. Really? Apple?
好, 听着. 有好的名字我们还可以换.
Right, listen. If we come up with something better, we'll change it.
先这么试试看看.
Let's just go with it and see if it sticks.
它最多能同时显示192个存储单元
It will display up to 192 memory locations
在荧幕上.
on the monitor simultaneously.
让我解释一下, 这个东东实际上超厉害的.
Allow me to explain because it's quite fascinating, actually.
它的逻辑电路板非常复杂, 尤其是与一些...
The logic board is rather complex, especially compared to some of
其他的电路板相比.
the other boards here, including of course,
连Altair也算上.
the Altair.
显而易见...
And as you can see...
它更加小巧, 便宜, 容易生产和组装...
it's much smaller, and cheaper to manufacture and build...
它采用的是动态随机存取记忆体, 所以我们可以...
which, by using dynamic RAM, I was able...
缩小主机板的尺寸.
We were able to shrink the size of the board substantially.
所以它可以连上电视用?
So, it works with your television?
对, 对, 对, 对头!
Yes. Yes, yes, yes!
任何电视或荧幕都行.
It will work on any television, or video monitor.
只需要配一个广播频率转换器
All you need is a radio frequency converter
你就能把处理器产生的图像
to display the images from your microprocessor
显示在外部荧幕上了.
to your set output device.
它能运行Basic编程语言哦.
And it'll run BASIC.
我觉得能跑Baisc编程语言是一大优点...
It will also run BASIC, which I think could be a great...
好吧, 就这样做总结吧, 谢谢大家.
So I guess that wraps it up. Thank you very much for your time.
很高兴来这里. 靠!
This was terrific. Fuck.
观众好冷淡.
Tough crowd.
晚安, 先生们. 我叫弗兰克...
Good evening, gentlemen. I'm Frank.
我叫鲁兹.
I'm Lutz.
我们在此展示无需繁杂手续设置计算CPU.
And we're here with reduced instruction set computing CPU.
打扰一下. 我叫保罗.特里尔.
Excuse me. Name is Paul Terrell.
我看了你们的展示.
I saw your presentation.
怎样?
And?
我想谈谈生意.
And I'd like to talk business.
- 怎么谈?  - 好...
- What can I do for you? - Well...
我在Mountainview市有家电脑配件店.
I own a local computer parts store, in Mountainview.
店名叫位元电脑商店?
The Byte Shop?
你购买电脑配件.
You buy computer parts.
是的, 我销售各类电子器件, 晶体管, 电焊设备, 屏幕之类的.
Yeah. We sell transistors, boards, soldering equipment, monitors.
你知道的, 兴趣使然的那种.
You know, hobbyist types.
像"灿坤"电气连锁店那样?
Like Radio Shack?
不.
No.
听着, 你来我店里看看就知道了.
Listen, why don't you stop by and talk to me some time.
这是我名片, 记得给我打电话.
There's my card. Give me a call.
很好.
Great.
很高兴见到你.
It was nice meeting you.
我叫史蒂夫.乔布斯.
Steve Jobs.
史蒂夫.乔布斯. 好!
Steve Jobs. All right.
那个人谁是啊?
Who was that?
- 那是保罗.特里尔 - 哦.
- It's Paul Terrell. - Oh.
谁?
Who?
你想要投资多少钱?
So what kind of investment are we talking about here?
天啊, 史蒂夫. 我只是说我有兴趣, 没说我想买.
Jesus, Steve. I said I was interested, not buying.
我知道, 但你不是唯一的对我们感兴趣的意向买家.
I know. But you're also not the only interested party.
- 啊, 不是吧? 我不是唯一的?  - 不是的.
- Oh, really? I'm not? - No.
- 你不是.  - 呣.
- You're not. - Hmm.
有点意思.
That's interesting.
那天晚上在Homebrew会场上的情况看起来可不乐观啊.
Because it sure seemed that way the other night at Homebrew.
你以为那是我们去的第一个会场吗?
You think that's the first stop that we made?
全硅谷我们都去过了.
We've been all over The Valley.
哦, 呃, 你已经找到了零售商.
Oh, well, then you already have a retailer.
有那么几个报价.
I got offers.
...听我说, 保罗. 我全名里面也有保罗(史蒂夫.保罗.乔布斯). 我爸也是.
Look, Paul. My middle name's Paul. My dad's name is Paul.
一群人叫保罗, 我...
Bunch of Pauls. I'm...
我认为, 我们有共同点.
I think we're kindred spirits here.
我们都是有着非凡直觉的商人.
We're both businessmen that operate from our gut.
直觉告诉我, 你应该抓住机会跟我们做生意.
And my gut tells me to give you this opportunity.
我考虑400美元一台, 要50台, 货到付款.
I'm thinking $400 per machine, for 50 units, paid at the time of delivery.
400美元一台, 定货100台, 预付三分之一的款.
$400 for a hundred units, a third up front.
我不想讨价还价.
We're not negotiating.
不, 我想.
Yes, we are.
好吧, 我付450美元一台, 450美元.
Okay. I'll pay $450 per machine. $450.
货到付款, 不预付. 我知道很有挑战, 史蒂夫.
On delivery, nothing up front. I know it's asking a lot, Steve.
这可是一大笔钱, 如果你能按时交货.
But it's a big payoff if you deliver.
我交货的时候...
When I deliver.
500美元一台就成交.
$500 per unit and you've got a deal.
好吧, 三个月内交货.
All right. You got 90 days.
两个月就够了.
I'll have it in 60.
丹尼尔和我没有地方了, 因此...
Daniel and I just didn't have room at our place, so...
不, 不. 我很高兴你能求我帮忙.
No, no. I'm glad you asked.
既然我们能帮忙...
Now we could...
把东西搬走, 再清理打扫一下.
move some things around, give it a good cleaning.
我会把我的工具搬到工具房里去.
I could move most of my tools to the shed.
热的时候再给你们弄台电风扇.
Maybe get you boys a fan when it gets hot.
哦.
Ooh.
怎么样?
What do you think?
太完美了, 老爸.
It's great, Dad.
是的. 这太棒了.
Yes. It is. This is perfect.
那就好, 希望你们能做点大事.
Good. Well, it'll be good to see you building something.
好了. 嘿, 保持整洁.
Good. Hey, keep it neat.
里里外外都要整洁.
Inside and out.
- 谢谢, 杰克先生.  - 呣.
- Thanks, Mr. J. - Mmm.
我们有自己的店面了.
We got a shop.
是的.
Yes, we do.
怎么样?
How's it going?
搞定.
Voila.
这应该直一点, 那个应该对称.
It's gotta be straighter. These have to be more symmetrical.
我们在两个月内要做50个主机板,
We have 60 days to complete 50 of these,
你还在意什么对称不对称吗?
and you're worried about the symmetry?
史蒂夫, 没有人会在意主板的样子.
Steve, nobody cares about the look of the board.
- 我在意.  - 好吧, 挺不错.
- I care. - Well, that's just great.
你夸口两个月就交货的时候, 我们就制定时间不多了.
But we were out of time the minute you made that stupid promise.
你说得对.
You're right.
我们需要人帮忙.
Need help.
- 沃兹... - 干嘛?
- Woz. - Huh?
- 我们有麻烦了.  - 呃?
- We got a problem. - Huh?
我们得想办法怎样安排这几个员工.
We got to figure out what to do with all these employees.
- 你认识比尔? - 比尔.
- You know Bill? - Bill.
- 好久不见, 沃兹.  - 最近怎样?
- Too long, Woz. - How are you?
很高兴见到你. 大家伙怎样?
Good to see you. How is everyone?
哦, 这位是我的朋友丹尼尔.阔特科.
Oh, this is my friend Daniel Kottke.
你好, 久仰大名. 最近怎样?
Hey. I've heard a lot about you. How're you doing?
克特科? 就是你和老乔一起去印度的, 当然知道你的大名.
Kottke? Kottke from India, of course.
对你, 我也是久仰大名.
I've heard a lot about you, too.
别碰.
Don't touch that.
这是克里斯, 就是我说过的邻居小孩?
That's Chris Espinosa. Kid down the street I was telling you about?
- 很高兴来这里, 伙计们.  - 太酷了.
- Nice to meet you, fella. - This is gonna be so cool.
不错, 很高兴你喜欢这里.
Great. I'm so glad that you're excited
喜欢我们正在做的事情.
about this thing we're doing here.
能私下聊两句吗?
Can I talk to you for a second?
可以.
Yeah.
对不起, 别动, 站一边去.
Excuse me, just please stop. And go over there.
别碍事, 都站一边去.
Just out of the way, over there.
我们目前请不起三个人.
We can't afford to pay three people right now.
我们自己都开不出工资, 除非我们按时交货.
We can't afford to pay ourselves, unless we deliver.
别管克里斯, 他就是一小屁孩, 他就是想(免费)帮忙.
And don't worry about Chris. He's just a kid. So he just wants to help.
你才是小屁孩.
You're just a kid.
笑一下...
Cheese!
谢了, 妈妈.
Thanks, Mom.
太冏了.
So embarrassing.
- 好了. - 说到做到.
- All right. - As promised.
这主机板不错.
Nice board.
其余的部分在哪儿?
Where's the rest?
其余的? 就这些了.
The rest? This is all of them.
我要的是50台电脑.
I asked for 50 computers.
包括键盘, 机壳, 屏幕, 电源等全部的东西.
That's keyboards, cases, monitors, and power included.
不是光秃秃的主机板.
Not just boards.
什么叫光秃秃的主机板? 这可是最新科技.
Just boards? Excuse me? Just boards? These are state-of-the-art.
我们的逻辑电路板是...没有人做得出来.
The logic boards alone are... Nobody's making anything like this.
他们是. 你怎么能这么说话?
They're, what, how dare you! How dare you!
我同事是想说...
I think what my colleague is saying is that...
你没看到这蕴藏的大好机会.
You're not seeing the possibilities here.
这实际上是一台令人难以置信的"强悍"的电脑.
That is indeed one unbelievably kick ass computer.
对顾客来说可不是.
Not to the consumer.
呃, 所以可能你的顾客
Well, then maybe your consumer
应该学学怎么用...
should start to learn how to...
怎么使用这种电脑, 不是吗?
How to even work that, don't you think?
听着, 兄弟.
Listen, boys.
你们卖给我的应该是一台完整电脑.  有键盘和荧幕的那种.
You sold me on a home computer. That's a keyboard and monitor.
这就一个主机板, 没了.
This is a board.
现在, 这是个不错的基础
Now, I'm sure this makes a very capable starter kit,
但对于一般用户,
but the everyday person,
不是工程师的那种人,
the kind of person that's not an engineer,
也不是向你一样的电脑俱乐部出身,
or in a computer club like you,
根本搞不懂这东西怎么用.
they're not gonna know what the hell this is.
一般用户根本不想学自己组装一台电脑.
The average Joe doesn't want to build their own computer.
他们只想买回去,
They just want to buy it.
拆开盒子, 插上电源,
They want to take it out of the box, plug it in,
就能用了.
and have it work.
你觉得呢, 史蒂夫?
Steve.
你有在听吗?
Are you listening to me?
是的, 这是你的主机板.
Yeah. These are your boards.
你一定能卖出去.
And they will sell.
我保证这点.
I can promise you that.
你不是看了我们在Homebrew的展示吗!
You saw our demo at Homebrew.
你知道加上一些外围设备, 这东西就能有多强悍.
You know what it's capable of with the right components,
而且, 这些外围设备, 你这里都有卖.
which, by the way, all of which you sell.
给客户展示一下.
So, demo it to the consumer.
而且外围设备可以单独卖钱.
And market the components separately.
你展示一下你店里的键盘, 荧幕.
You show them your keyboards, and your monitors.
客户会在店里买这些配件, 你赚的更多,
You'll move more inventory that way,
你会赚到很多很多的现金美钞.
and you'll make a hell of a lot more cash.
其实你赚到了.
You got me.
好吧, 史蒂夫.
All right, Steve.
我会试试出售.
I'll try to sell them.
如果卖不出去, 我就不会再下单了.
But if I don't, I'm not making another order.
好, 没问题.
Okay. That's fine.
但是你肯定会对我们的第二代机型有兴趣.
But I think that you might be really interested in our second model.
二代机型是什么?
What's the second model?
你说什么?
What are you talking about?
一体成型机.
All-in-one.
有什么事?
Can I help you?
我是罗德.霍尔特.
Yeah, I'm Rod Holt.
工程技师. 我们电话里谈过.
The technician. We talked on the phone.
当然. 你是罗德.
Of course. It's Rod.
谢谢你过来一趟.
Glad you could stop by.
欢迎来到Apple电脑公司.
Welcome to Apple Computer.
好吧.
All right.
带我看看所谓的革命性的"东东".
Show me this revolutionary piece of shit.
Apple II 电脑.
The Apple ll.
这是世界上第一台一体机.
It's the first ever all-in-one personal home computer.
你叫我来干什么?
And you called me because?
我们需要你设计一个高效率的电源. 机箱里面用的.
We need a heat efficient power supply. In the case.
我觉得根本不可能, 但是我不介意(试试).
That's impossible, but don't mind me.
毕竟, 我也是个工程师.
I'm just, you know, an engineer.
需要多大电压?
So, wattage?
40瓦, 而且必须安静.
40 watts. And quiet.
- 怎样算是"安静"?  - 最好是静音的.
- What the hell do you mean, quiet? - I mean silent.
目前还没有这种东东.
There's no such thing.
它会发热, 必须有个风扇.
These things run hot. They need fans in them.
风扇噪音可不会小.
Those bitches ain't quiet.
这就是为什么我们需要要你来...
That's exactly why we need you.
重新设计.
To redesign it.
- 重新设计什么?
Redesign what?
整个电源系统. 重新开始设计.
The power supply. From scratch.
不能有风扇, 还要保证散热.
It can't have a fan, it can't overheat.
还要能装进机壳, 就这么大的机壳.
And it needs to fit inside a box, this size.
别抽烟, 好吗!
Don't do that. Please, don't do...
不管怎样, 尽你可能做吧.
Whatever. Do whatever you want.
我薪水是200美元一天.
My rate is $200 a day.
而且我觉得不爽就闪人.
And if I ever think things aren't working out, I walk.
呣-呣.
Mmm-hmm.
你清楚吗?
Are we clear?
明白.
We're clear.
我们是在说朝阳产业.
We're talking about the future.
这市场还没人开始做.
We're working in a market that doesn't even exist yet.
Intel在处理器行业做的很大,
What Intel has done for the microprocessor,
我们将在个人电脑领域做同样的事情.
we are gonna do for the home computer.
你怎么听不懂呢?
How can you not know what I'm talking about?
不, 夫人, 它能在荧幕上显示东西.
No, ma'am. But it runs on a TV monitor.
是, 没错, 就像电视机.
Yes, like a television set. Exactly.
我认为你可能没明白我的意思, 它不是电视.
I don't think you understand. It's not a TV.
它是个人电脑.
It's a personal computer.
好吧, 你有打字机吗
Okay, do you own a typewriter?
好, 你平时会用吗? 很好.
Great. Okay, now do you use it? Perfect.
想像你有一台接上电视的打字机.
So imagine combining your typewriter with your television set.
等等, 等等.
No. Don't... Wait. Wait!
等等. 先生, 别挂. 请别挂断电话.
Wait. Please, sir, don't, don't hang up.
是, 没错, 我们现在规模很小, 但是我们...
Yes. We are small right now, but we...
你怎么知道我们在车库里工作?
How do you know we're working out of our garage?
谁告诉你的?
Who told you that?
啊!
Ahhh!
是, 是.
Yes. Yes.
谢谢你肯花时间听我说.
Well, thank you for taking the time.
是的, 先生, Apple电脑公司.
Yes, sir. Apple Computer.
Apple...水果那个Apple.
Apple? Yes, like the fruit.
那是谁?
Who's that?
不, 不. 我只是想让你过来看一眼.
No. No. All I'm asking is that you come visit us.
就看一眼, 你绝对会感兴趣.
One meeting and I promise you'll be on board.
我觉得大概5万美元.
Around $50,000 would be my guess.
喂?
Hello?
他们说什么?
What did they say?
这些人到底怎么回事?
What the hell is the matter with people?
看来电话打得不顺利.
Take it the call went well.
我本来想说噎死你, 但是反正这种垃圾食物早晚会害死你.
I would say I hope you choke, but that burrito is gonna kill you either way.
放轻松, 史蒂夫.
Oh, come on, Steve.
再说一遍, 伙计.
Cool your jets, man.
你太紧张了, 放松一下.
Excuse you?
只是, 你知道的, 你太紧张了.
Just, you know, you're so stressed, you know?
就像为了改变而放松下来.
It's, like, relax for a change.
为了改变...为什么? 为了跟你俩个混蛋一样.
For a change... Why? Why? So I can be more like you two assholes?
嘿, 我正在学习"嵌入式电路".
Hey. I'm studying integrated circuit design here, man.
是吗?
Are you?
我们都在做各自该做的事.
We each do our part.
是吗? 我怎么觉得你做的事都是没用的?
Really? Then why do I suddenly feel like your part is expendable?
别像在印度的时候那样抽烟了. 醒醒吧, 我们不在印度了.
Out here smokin' up like we're in India. Well, wake up! We're not.
你怎么了?
What happened to you?
- 你曾经很有活力的... - 什么? 我曾经怎么啦?
- You used to be... - What? I used to be what?
- 自我激励.  - 我就是自我激励.
- Motivated. - I am motivated.
是吗? 表现给我看啊.
Really? Then show me.
这是生意! 丹尼尔, 振作点.
This is a business, Daniel.
你要是自己不努力, 我也束手无策.
And I can't help you if you don't help yourself.
我每天打100个电话.
I'm in there making a hundred phone calls.
罗德.霍尔特在做苦力.
Rod is slaving away.
那小鬼也总能找到事情做,
The kid always finds something to do,
沃兹每天也超努力的.
and God knows Woz pulls his weight.
谢谢夸奖.
Thank you.
每天超努力地增肥.
And that's a whole lot of weight.
真是的...人家心里很受伤的.
That really... That kind of hurts my feelings.
哦.
Whoa.
我没走错吧...
Is this the right...
这是Apple电脑公司?
Apple Computer?
- 是, 正是我们.  - 没错.
- Yeah, this is us. - Yeah.
你以为会看到别的景象?
You expecting something else?
没, 嗯, 也许没想到有这么多宅男.
Uh, no. Well, yeah, maybe something a little less Manson Family.
- 我们还在创业的起步阶段. - 是的.
- It's a startup. - Yeah.
我叫麦克.马库拉.
I'm Mike Markkula.
我是史蒂夫.乔布斯.
Steve. Jobs.
史蒂夫, 久仰大名.
Steve. I heard a lot about you.
董.瓦伦泰恩在电话里提过你.
You spoke to Don Valentine on the phone.
我们是老同事.
He and I are old colleagues of sorts.
Atari的投资人.
The VC from Atari.
是的, 瓦伦泰恩. 他说你打了150多通电话给他.
Yeah, Valentine. He said you called him 150 times.
我靠, 服了你了.
Jesus.
他差点跪下来求我, 要我过来看一眼.
He practically begged me to come and look at your outfit here.
我就当帮他个忙吧.
Called in a personal favor.
那好, 马克.
Well, Mark.
是麦克.
Mike.
麦克.
欢迎来到Apple电脑公司.
Welcome to Apple Computer.
谢谢了. 是的, 这是? ...
Thank you. Yeah, is this...
这就是你所有的家当?
This is everything?
- 是的.  - 才怪.
- Yes. - No.
不. 我们在更好的位置还有6家零售店.
No. We're, we're in six stores in the greater area.
我们大约一个月内会发布Apple II 电脑.
We'll be launching the Apple ll in about a month.
- 还有好几个月.  - 很接近.
- In a few months. - It's close.
各位, 有地方能坐下来好好谈谈吗?
Gentlemen, is there some place we can talk?
这是你的.
Here you are, fellas.
For you.
史蒂夫是素食主义者, 狂吃水果.
Steve's a fruitarian. He will only eat fruit.
好啦, 你们谈生意吧.
Okay, boys. I'll just... I'll leave you to your business.
谢谢.
Thank you.
- 谢谢啦, 妈.  - 谢谢夫人.
- Thanks, Mom. - Thanks, Mrs. J.
你是最棒的.
You're the best.
耶, 我们说到哪了?
Yeah. So where were we?
不好意思, 不要南辕北辙了, 你从哪冒出来的?
I'm sorry, don't take this the wrong way, but what's your angle?
呃...
Uh...
我同事想问的是...
What my colleague is trying to say is...
你之前在哪里工作?
Where was your last employment?
英特尔.
Intel.
你想投资多少?
So how much are we talking about here?
- 什么, 投资?  - 你不就是为了这个来的.
- What, the investment? - That's what you came here for.
史蒂夫不会说客套话.
Foreplay is not Steve's strong suit.
我没说错吧?
Isn't it?
耶, 嗯,
Yeah, well,
我在找一个真正值得投资的东西.
I've been looking for something to really sink my teeth into.
听着, 史蒂夫. 我愿意冒险.
Look, Steve. I'm willing to take the risk.
这个公司看起来值得冒险.
And, this certainly qualifies.
但是要能保证我不会平白承担风险.
But risk disguised as promise.
我知道你是个有担当的. 我看得出来.
And you've shown promise. I've seen it in your eye,
我看得出来, 因为我跟你一样.
and I know that look because I've had it myself.
直觉告诉我, 你会有大作为.
Tells me you're on to something big.
好, 说正经的.
Yeah. Okay. To the point.
我想先投资9万美元.
I think we should start with around 90 grand,
看看这笔投资的结果如何.
see where that takes us.
行, 对不起. 你能再说一遍吗?
Okay, I'm sorry. Could you repeat that?
不好意思.
I'm sorry.
9万美元可能不够.
$90,000 isn't gonna get it done.
哦, 史蒂夫, 等等.
Oh, whoa, whoa. Wait. Steve, one second.
还有别人会跑到一个车库里投资吗?
I don't see anybody else coming in your garage with a checkbook.
不, 不是这意思.
Oh, no, no.
9万美元对我们是够了.
Ninety grand gets it done for us.
我是怕你将来后悔投资的太少.
I just don't think it gets it done for you.
我们先从9万美元开始算吧.
We'll do the $90,000 investment.
公司总值估30万美元.
At a $300,000 valuation.
我需要你再投入25万美元作为贷款
But I also want you to kick in a $250,000 credit line
按10%的利息计算
with 10% interest to be paid back in full
盈利后, 连本带利还你.
once we meet net revenue positive.
好.
Okay.
我说了, 好啊
What I mean is, okay.
是的.
Yeah.
现在, 你们必须做的第一件事情是...
Now, the first thing you need to do
正式成立公司, 这样你们两个创始人, 才能保护好自己的财产.
is incorporate, so that you two as owners can protect your interest.
当然, 前提是你们同意让我加入.
And that is, of course, if you'll have me aboard.
谢谢, 马库拉先生.
Thank you very much, Mr. Markkula.
嗯, 叫我麦克就好...
Of course. Mike. Yeah.
- 你好吗?  - 是的, 放那儿.
- How're you doing? - Yeah, put her there.
- 比尔.  - 比尔?
- Bill. - Bill?
- 费尔南德兹.  - 是的.
- Fernandez. - Yeah.
- 哦, 谢了, 麦克.  - 耶.
- Oh. Thanks, Mike. - Yeah.
史蒂夫, 你很厉害啊.
Steve. Here's to you, pal.
你有在听吗?
Are you even listening to me?
我怀孕了.
I'm pregnant.
史蒂夫, 说话啊.
Steve, you have to talk to me.
这也是你的责任啊.
This is your responsibility, too.
你敢
Don't you dare
怪我身上啊?
blame this on me.
- 我没有.  - 呣呣.
- I'm not. - Mmm-mmm.
我们都有过别的...
We both had our moments of...
你指什么?  你究竟在说什么?
What? What the hell are you talking about?
你.
You.
我在印度的时候, 你有别的男人吧? 你懂得.
When I was in India, you were with, you know.
史蒂夫, 你疯了吗? 你不能全赖给我啊.
Steve? Are you crazy? You cannot put this all on me.
你现在不能把这事瘫在我头上. 现在不行.
You can't do this to me right now. Not now.
呃, 对不起, 这不是你计划中的事.
Well, I'm sorry this isn't part of your plan.
对不起, 那是你的问题, 不是我的.
I'm sorry you have a problem.
问题不是我的.
But it's not happening to me.
- 但, 这是你的孩子... - 不是!
- But this is your... - No!
滚出我的房子.
Get out of my house.
- 什么?  - 马上滚!
- What? - Now!
哦, 天啦. 终于到这一天了.
Oh, Jesus. Here we go.
嘿. 你一切还好吧?
Hey. Is everything okay out here?
史蒂文他要把我赶出去.
Steven, he's kicking me out.
他不想与我有丝毫干系了.
He doesn't want anything to do with me.
或许这样对你更好些.
Maybe it's for the best.
但是他不应该这样对你.
You don't deserve to be treated the way he treats you.
- 我怀孕了, 丹尼尔.
I'm pregnant, Daniel.
什么? 你有了...
What? You're...
他说孩子不是他的, 但是我从没有外遇...
He says it's not his, but I would never...
我做错了什么?
What did I do wrong?
你没有做错什么.
You didn't do anything wrong.
错的是史蒂夫.
It's Steve.
就是他错了...
That's just him.
他变了.
He changed.
和你的电视机连接起来.
Hook them right to your television.
就是这样, 耶.
It is, yeah.
你觉得怎么样, J? 准备好了吗?
What do you think, J? Ready?
女士们, 先生们, 我是史蒂夫.乔布斯.
Ladies and gentlemen, my name is Steve Jobs.
当我创立Apple的时候,
When I founded this company,
我心中只有一个目标.
I had one goal in mind.
而且没有人觉得这个目标可以实现.
And that was to do what nobody else considered possible.
(那就是)将世界最尖端科技的力量和艺术
To put the power and the beauty
完美结合做成产品
of the world's most advanced technology
并将它带到老百姓的生活中去.
in the hands and homes of people just like you and me.
我保证, 从今天开始,
And I can promise you that after today,
你们看待电脑的眼光将彻底改变.
you will never look at computers the same way again.
因此, 我自豪地想你们和泉世界宣布,
So I am proud to introduce to you, and the world,
这就是个人电脑的未来.
the future of personal computing.
革命性的Apple II (苹果二代电脑).
The revolutionary Apple ll.
我们得重来, 整个操作必须有直觉性,
Gotta just start over. It has to be intuitive.
可预测性. 我是说, 在你们了解你将做什么之前,
Precognitive. I mean, I want it to know what you want to do
你们得让你的产品知道你将怎样对待它.
before you even know you want to do it.
等等, 我们还是在聊"命令栏"的事吗?
Wait, are we still talking about the command prompts?
比尔, 我们在谈所有的细节, 整件事情.
Bill, we're talking about everything. The whole thing.
"丽莎". 伙计们, 我现在告诉你们: 这个产品, 代表着未来.
Lisa. Guys, it's the future. I'm telling you right now.
我是说, "丽莎"在未来10年内将改变世界.
I mean, Lisa's gonna do for the next 10 years
就像Apple II在过去3年里改变了世界一样.
what the Apple ll did for the last three.
我现在就可以这样说道.
I can tell you that right now.
你知道人们为什么买苹果电脑吗?
Do you know why people buy an Apple?
为什么买苹果电脑, 而不买我们竞争对手的产品?
Why do they buy an Apple, not the competitor?
因为它(苹果电脑)很酷.
Because it's got bravado.
它代表社会地位, 让你成为时尚风标.
It's social status.
不, 你们知道怎么回事吗? 它甚至比这更重要.
No, you know what? It's even more than that.
它是社会流通货币.
It's social currency.
我们提高了业界产品水准.
We've raised the bar.
如果我们想保持领先, 我们要勇于冒险.
And if we want to stay there, we gotta risk everything.
像狄伦, 毕卡索, 牛顿这样的伟大创作者, 他们都勇于承担失败的风险
Great artists, Dylan, Picasso, Newton, they risk failure.
我们做大事, 就要敢冒风险.
And if we want to be great, we've gotta risk it, too.
为了一个命令栏,
On the command bar?
为了所有事情.
On everything.
- 什么... - 从小事情开始.
- What... - And it starts with the little things.
这里有20多个功能
There's over 20 different functions
命令栏的改变虽小, 但是牵一发而动全身
tied to every single variation of the command bar,
(就这小的改变)也要花好几个星期去编程.
which by the way, takes weeks to program.
我们不会重复IBM做过的东西
We're not doing anything that IBM's not already doing.
我相信我们的前瞻性
And I would rather gamble on our vision
远胜于做一件雷同的产品.
than make a me-too product.
我们做出的产品虽然很小, 但是总是令人难忘.
We got to make the small things just unforgettable.
简而言之, 就是这款"丽莎文字处理器".
Let's just start with something simple. LisaWrite.
我点击这些选单会出现什么?
What happens if I click on one of these tabs?
会有下拉选单, 让你能进入"参数设定"的界面,
You get a drop-down menu, and then there's preferences,
和"页面设置"界面.
and page options.
好, 正是如此.
Okay. Exactly.
现在, 点击哪个选单可以修改字体?
Now, which tab do I click on to get different font styles?
"丽莎文字处理器"支持几种客户自定义字体?
How many custom typefaces are there on LisaWrite?
我正是我想跟你说的一件事, 史蒂夫, 那就是...
That's actually something that I wanted to talk to you about, Steve, is...
几个月前我就要求你们弄出多种字体,
I've been asking for the fonts for months.
但你要求的东西都是概念层面的.
But everything we're talking about is conceptual.
对不起, 但是目前字体还不是至关紧要的事情.
And I'm sorry, but typeface, it isn't exactly a pressing issue right now.
每一件事都至关紧要.
Everything is a pressing issue.
如果你想把"丽莎"所代表的未来变成现实,
If we want to make the vision for Lisa a reality,
你就要全心投入, 才能做出伟大的产品.
we gotta put in the hours and make something great.
我知道, 但是这个软件做起来很困难,
Yeah, but we have a hard date on this software,
而且弄些漂亮字体还是于事无补.
and I'm sorry, but adding pretty fonts is not gonna change that.
比尔, 你说呢?
Well, Bill?
如果你不能共享我们的热忱,
If you don't share our enthusiasm,
不认同这家公司的理念...
and care for the vision of this company...
不, 不, 不, 不, 我只是不太我理解...
No, no, no, no. I just, I'm not understanding...
- 滚出去.  - 什么?
- Get out. - What?
- 要你卷铺盖走人. - 什么? 等等...
- Get your shit and get out. - What, wait...
- 你玩完了. - 什么? 你竟然...
- You're done. - What, you...
什么, 你难道, 你难道想炒我鱿鱼吗?
What, are you gonna, you're gonna fire me?
不!
No!
我已经炒了你鱿鱼!
I already fired you!
你怎么还赖着不走?
Why are you still here?
史蒂夫, 那是我们部门最好的程序设计师.
Steve, he was our best programmer in the division.
这个最好的程序设计师并不关心我们的公司理念.
He's the best programmer that doesn't care about our vision.
好吧, 我知道我不该说这些, 但是...
Okay. Look, I know it's not my place to say it, but...
那就闭上你的臭嘴, 比尔!
Then shut the hell up, Bill!
耶.
Yeah.
不好意思, 打扰了, 乔布斯先生.
So sorry to interrupt you, Mr. Jobs,
你的律师8点就来了.
but your attorney is here for your 8:00.
好.
All right.
今天下午我就要看到样本.
I want to see samples this afternoon.
我们居然做了个没有字体的文字处理软件.
Somehow we managed to design a word processor that doesn't have fonts.
再也不能这样了.
And it can't happen again.
赶快给我搞定!
So fix it!
2点至3点. 你10点的安排的事情正等着你去解决.
2:00 to 3:00. And your 10:00 is waiting for you.
史蒂夫. 史蒂夫, 嘿.
Steve. Steve, hey.
丹尼尔, 嘿.
Daniel. Hey.
能跟你聊两句吗?
Do you have a second to talk?
我以为我们得重新预约吧.
I thought we rescheduled.
就一会儿.
It'll only take a second.
大家都这么说.
That's what everyone says.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
好吧.
Fine.
我还没吃午饭, 所以中午去"好地球"餐厅一起吃个便饭.
I don't have a lunch, so, meet me at Good Earth at noon.
好啊, 没问题.
Okay. Cool. Okay.
你最近负责什么工作?
What are you working on these days?
哦, 呃...
Oh, um...
主要是Apple II电脑的维修手册.
Apple ll Plus repairs, mainly.
好.
Right.
你得签这个.
I need you to sign this.
从法律意义上讲它可以保证你的探视权.
It legally preserves your visitation rights.
我不需要. 丽莎.布热南不是我的孩子.
I don't want them. Lisa Brennan is not my child.
法庭不这么认为.
The courts disagree.
她跟很多人乱搞, 孩子肯定不是我的. 至少不太可能是我的.
Chris-Ann is a lunatic. It's impossible. At the very least, improbable.
你知道做个亲子鉴定
You knew going into this
就能知道你是不是亲生父亲.
the paternity test could prove that you were the father.
加州有2千4百万人口.
There are 24 million people in California.
亲子鉴定有5%的测试误差.
That test has a five percent margin of error.
因此120万人都有可能是那个孩子的爸爸.
That's 1.2 million people that could be the father of that child.
而且我不是孩子的爸爸.
And it's not me.
你说服我也没用, 关键是你得签这个名.
You don't need to convince me. But you do need to sign this.
布热南小姐要求你付赡养费.
Miss Brennan is entitled to your child support
不管你签不签这个字都一样.
regardless of whether you sign it or not.
你真的要放弃你的探视...
Do you really want to give up the rights to see your...
她的女儿的权利?
To see her child in the future?
我没时间.
I don't have time.
现在不行.
Not now.
史蒂夫, 身为人父, 我拜托你签一下字.
Steven, as a father, I implore you to sign this.
不管你认不认丽莎是你女儿.
Regardless of whether you think Lisa is your daughter or not.
签字没有风险.
There's no risk in signing.
不签, 你倒是有可能后悔.
Only the regret if you don't.
弗里德里克.罗德.霍尔特, 他最近
Frederick Rodney Holt, he recently made
追加认购了
an additional preferred purchase
106,656股(以每股19美分的价格).
of 106,656 shares at 19 cents a share.
好吧, 明确地讲, 这些新认购的股票
Right, and to be clear, this new purchase,
并不影响霍尔特先生
it does not affect Mr. Holt's entitlement
作为公司创始人的权益股票.
to founder stock.
不, 绝不. 史蒂夫?
No, not at all. Steve?
不, 不, 不. 罗德.霍尔特得到了他应得的权益了.
No, no, no. Rod gets his due.
丹尼尔.克特克,
Daniel Kottke,
工程技师, 我们的创始人之一. 在上次的会议上,
engineering technician, founding employee. Now, at our last meeting I,
我不认为我们达成了一致意见
I don't believe that we met a consensus
就是有关丹尼尔是否拥有创始人权益股票的问题.
as to Mr. Kottke's entitlement to founder stock.
呃, 实话实说, 给丹尼尔...
Well, in all honesty, to be rewarding Daniel
和霍尔特一样多股份的话, 对霍尔特来说...
with the same amount of stock as Rod seems
有点不公平, 是不是?
a bit unfair. Doesn't it?
没错, 丹尼尔没有股份.
Yes. Daniel gets nothing.
没有股份?
Nothing?
你确定要这么做
Don't you think you should
你为你的决定再思考一下吗?
think about what you're doing, for a second?
我想过了, 丹尼尔没有股份.
I have thought about it. Daniel gets nothing.
明白, 先生.
Yes, sir.
事情已经很明显了...
It's noted.
什么?
What?
随便一个初级工程师就能取代他.
Any low grade technician could do his job.
我白养了他很多年了. 不能感情用事.
I've been feeding him for years. It's not personal.
去你的感情用事, 史蒂夫. 他是你兄弟耶.
Don't give me that bullshit, Steve. Of course it's personal.
他做现在的事都很吃力.
He can barely do his job.
如果我们给丹尼尔股份,
If we give Daniel preferred stock,
那些让比他强10倍的工程师情何以堪.
some engineer with 10 times his talent gets nothing.
然后, 你猜怎么着?
Then what happens?
我们现在就把原则定好, 行吗?
Then we just draw this line right here, right now, okay?
所以你在说些什么呢? 管理之道, 还是...
So you, what are you talking about? Management, or...
管理层和工程师.
Management and engineers.
是的. 这意味着...
Yeah, this means...
我真的了解, 麦克.
I know what it means, Mike.
谢谢.
Thanks.
- 不, 他是... - 你知道的, 我不知道...
- No, he's... - You know what, I don't...
好, 我们继续吗?
Okay then. Shall we continue?
我们可以假定比尔.费尔南德兹,
We can assume that Bill Fernandez,
冉迪.威根屯
Randy Wiggington
和克里斯.艾斯品诺撒将不会
and Chris Espinosa will not
得到
be receiving
股票选择权吗?
any Options?
喝啤酒啊?
Drinking a beer, huh?
明天是你的大日子.
Tomorrow's a big day for you.
我们的大日子.
For us.
嗯, 我们的.
麦克跟我说了你做的好事, 关于比尔, 丹尼尔
Mike told me about what happened with Bill and Dan
还有克里斯. 好, 史蒂夫...
and Chris. And, Steve...
你为什么这么做?
Why'd you do it?
公司大了, 就对他们不管不顾了
The company outgrew them.
他们不是管理阶层. 他们也不是项目带头人.
They're not management. They're not project leads.
我的工作不是当好人.
It's not my job to be nice to people.
是为了让公司变得更好.
It's my job to make them better.
他们不值那个价.
They don't deserve it.
那谁就值那个价了?
Then who the hell does?
你知道公司怎么运转吗?
Do you know how this company works?
你想知道吗?
Do you want to know?
如果你想知道, 我可以教你.
I'd be happy to teach you, if you want to know.
你知道我当初为什么跟你一起创办这个公司吗?
Do you know why I started this company with you?
而放弃了惠普那个安稳工作吗?
Why I left the safety of HP for this?
你不知道吧, 你也没问过.
I doubt you do. You never asked.
我离开那里, 因为Apple是我亲手创办的.
I left because this was my thing.
还因为你们这些家伙很酷.
And you guys thought it was cool.
我只是想成为你们这帮酷男中的一份子.
I just wanted to be one of the guys.
而你是最酷的那个人.
And of all the guys I knew, you were the coolest.
你聪明而机灵
You were smart, quick-witted.
这就是我能以所好为生的机会.
And this was my chance to do what I loved.
我为了乐趣而加入,
And to do it for fun.
这就是全部, 这就是我想要的.
That's all, that's all I ever wanted.
我曾经以为这也是你想要的.
I thought that's what you wanted, too.
你变了, 史蒂夫.
Something's happened to you, Steve.
我长大了, 沃兹.
I'm grown up, Woz.
不, 不, 你还是个小屁孩.
No. No, you're not.
现在播报今日头条新闻
And now, turning to big news in business,
Apple公司又上头条新闻了.
Apple Incorporated is making headlines once again.
科技巨擘Apple公司
On Wall Street the tech titan Apple
今天上午上市了, 市场利润可观,
went public this morning, to incredible market interest,
新股上市的460万份股票
as four point six million shares of its IPO
在股市开盘后一小时内被认购一空.
were sold within an hour of the opening bell.
虽然华尔街高管们早预测到了
Wall Street executives had forecast the big day
今天是这个成长性科技公司的大日子.
for the growing technology company,
但是专家们还是表示Apple公司今天的表现
but experts now say Apple's day
还是大大超出所有人的狂热预期.
exceeded the market's wildest expectations.
它几乎是...年来最牛气的股票...
It was the most over...
嘿, 嘿, 就是他了!
Hey, hey. Here he is!
耶, 耶. 哦, 太好了.
Yeah. Yeah. Oh, terrific.
耶, 你成功了.
Yeah, you did it.
让我们一起把这股票做起来.
Let's help them move that stock.
嘿, 伙计.
Hey, pal.
哦, 嘿, 谢谢你.
Oh, hey, thank you.
生意如常, 伙计.
Business as usual, guys.
大伙儿, 还有点工作要做.
There's work to be done, people.
谢谢你. 我有一些很好玩的点子.
Thank you. I had some fun ideas.
我就是我分内的, 比尔. 后会有期.
This is it for me, Bill. I'll see you when I see you.
我要离开了.
I'm gonna get out of here.
有空打电话给你.
I'll call you later.
好的.
All right.
嗨, 你能通知马库拉先生我们来了吗? 谢谢.
Hi. Could you please tell Mr. Markkula we're here. Thank you.
好的, 洛克先生.
Yes, sir, Mr. Rock.
先生们.
Gentlemen.
麦克. 请.
Mike. Please.
坐吧.
Have a seat.
有些事情, 我们需要谈谈,
There's something we need to talk about,
尽管我知道你不想听.
and I don't think you're gonna like it.
是关于史蒂夫的.
It's Steve.
他在一个不切实际的项目上疯狂砸钱
He's hemorrhaging the company's dollar
而这个项目用我们的丽萨电脑是搞不定的.
on fantasies that simply are not possible with the Lisa computer.
但史蒂夫一直以来都善于化腐朽为神奇,
Yeah, but Steve's been doing the impossible
从公司在车库里创立以来就是这样的.
ever since this company was in a garage.
麦克, 你知道我欣赏史蒂夫的一切特质的, 真的.
Mike, I love everything Steve represents. You know that.
但我们在放纵他, 让他成了任性的孩子.
But he's like a kid in a candy store, and we've given him the keys.
是, 但这是他的公司, 他爱谁谁.
Yeah. But, it's his candy store.
没有人见过这种电脑,
You're never gonna see a personal computer
能把键盘和机身连在一起.
where the keyboard is attached to the machine again.
麦克, 问题很大.
Mike, it's a problem.
最大的问题是他还揶揄IBM公司.
The bigger problem is that he is ridiculing IBM.
乔布斯他买断了华尔街日报的一个整幅版面
Jobs took out a full page ad in The Wall Street Journal
公然挑衅世界上最大的电脑公司.
taunting the biggest computer company on the planet.
"恭喜你们终于做了一台个人电脑. "
"Congratulations on your first personal computer."
他这是要跟IBM开战啊.
He's trying to start a war with IB fucking M!
我看到这广告了.
I'm fully aware of the ad.
那你还不阻止他!
Then do something about it!
听着, 亚瑟, 你知道他是对的.
Listen, Arthur, you know he's right.
3年前, IBM对个人电脑根本没兴趣.
Three years ago IBM had no interest in the personal computer
现在你看看他们的样子.
and now look at 'em!
现在他们开始跟风了, 想想吧.
They followed us. Think about it.
我们想好了, 麦克.
We have, Mike.
令人抱歉的是, 董事会一致同意...
And I'm sorry, but the Board is unanimous.
史蒂夫不能再负责"丽萨"项目了.
Steve will no longer be involved in Lisa's development. Period.
怎么回事, 亚瑟? 你们要搞权力架空吗?
What is this, Arthur? Some sort of power play?
你们支持他搞这个有一年半了.
For 18 months now you've offered nothing but support.
这个节骨眼上要换掉他?
And now you want to try and take Jobs off of his own team?
我也不想呀, 麦克.
I don't want any of this, Mike.
但你得考虑一下...
But you have to try to look at it
站在股东角度考虑一下.
from the shareholder's perspective.
史蒂夫很棒.
Steve is great.
他很棒.  是的, 他真的很棒.
He's great. Yeah, he's great.
但他是个定时炸弹.
But he's a time bomb.
我们的职责就是拆掉这颗炸弹.
And it's our job to diffuse him.
那你去搞定这事儿.
So take care of it.
我才不管董事会的狗屁想法.
I don't give a shit what the Board thinks.
你可以在别的项目上发挥专长了. 就是, 就是说...
It's the time you're taking. Your perfectionism. It's, it's, it...
股东们一直盯着这产品,
They're looking at losses in the millions
自从立项以来, 我们就已经亏了几百万了.
before this thing even gets off the ground.
你们看不到全貌.
They're not seeing the big picture.
没错, 股东们都是急功近利.
That's right. The shareholders don't see past their own shadows.
他们只关心此时此刻.
They're only concerned about the here and the now.
董事会也同样"一叶障目不见森林".
And the Board has got blinders on.
如果他们的看法与你一致, 他们就不会吹毛求疵了,
If they could see you they'd take them off,
但是他们的看法跟我对你的看法不同,
they'd see you the way I see you.
他们的看法跟你的同事对你的看法也不同.
The way your employees see you.
"丽萨"是我自己的项目.
Lisa is my project.
它是我的.
It's mine.
董事会就这样从我手里抢走吗?
And they're taking it away from me?
你就让他们任意剥夺我的权力?
You're letting them take it away from me.
我靠, 史蒂夫. 你知道这不是事实.
Bullshit, Steve. You know that's not true.
他妈的.
Shit.
和其它电脑相比较,
There are more Apple IIs teaching more subjects
Apple II 电脑能教更多课程了.
in more schools than any other computer...
小到学前班的识字课程,
Everything from alphabet lessons for preschool,
大到大学的科学课程.
to science programs for graduate school.
所以无论布莱恩想成为什么,
So whatever Brian wants to be,
一台苹果个人电脑
an Apple personal computer
总是可以帮他实现梦想.
can help him be it.
Apple II 电脑 - 只有你想不到, 没有它做不到!
The AppleII. There's no telling how far it can take you.
看起来毫无道理.
Now that doesn't make any sense.
呃, 你还没像我一样见到如此多的谋杀, 克罗斯先生.
Well, you haven't seen as much of murder as I have, Mr. Cross.
我宁愿法官大人强迫我做这件事.
I'd rather have a judge give me the works than have to do it myself.
就在这儿我独自承担.
Right here in solitary.
那又怎样?
So what?
那样的话, 你正还是在惩罚我. 你也脱不了干系.
So you go right on punishing yourself. You can't get away with it.
嗨, 我是格比.卡普兰.
Hi, I'm Gabe Kaplan.
参加百事可乐挑战赛. 让你的口感决定一切.
Take the Pepsi Challenge. Let your taste decide.
不错吧, 伙计们. 好了, 现在你们可以告诉我了
Right, guys? Okay, now why don't you tell me
你们的选择. 百事可乐.
which one you chose. Pepsi Cola.
- 喂?  - 史蒂夫, 我是麦克.
- Yeah? - Hey, Steve. It's Mike.
嘿.
Hey.
嘿. 我想我给你找到了一个不错的项目.
Hey. Um, I think I may have found a project for you.
是研发部门正在搞的一个项目.
It's more of an R&D outcast than anything,
但是那实际上是你前一段时间批准的一个项目.
but it's actually a project you approved some time back.
不如你去看看吧?
Why don't you look into it?
这是"麦金托什"部门.
So this is the Macintosh team.
呣-呣.
Mmm-hmm.
哦, 天哪.
Oh, Jesus.
不. 只有史蒂夫.
Nope. It's just Steve.
见到你真高兴, 史蒂夫.
It's really good to see you, Steve.
比尔.阿特肯森. 很高兴他们得到了一员五虎上将.
Bill Atkinson. It's good to see they got A players over here.
呣-呣. 嘿, 起床.
Mmm-hmm. Hey. Get up.
嘿, 史蒂夫.乔布斯.
Hi, Steve Jobs.
你叫什么?
What's your name?
伯... 伯勒尔.史密斯.
Burr... Burrell Smith.
伯勒尔.史密斯.
Burrell Smith.
不好意思, 有点乱.
Oh, sorry for the mess.
我们就是一帮颓废青年. 因此...
We're just a bunch of degenerates. So...
没事, 我也喜欢颓废的苟活着.
It's okay. I like degenerates.
耶.
Yeah.
谁是项目负责人?
Who's your project lead?
呃, 杰夫.拉斯肯...
Uh, Jef Raskin...
我不知道他跑哪里去了.
I don't know where he is.
杰夫.拉斯肯.
Jef Raskin.
好. 我来处理. 现在由我负责了.
Okay. I'll deal with that one. I'll be taking over now.
呃...对不起, 你要执掌整个"麦金托什"项目?
Um... Sorry, taking over, like, the entire Macintosh project?
- 对.  - 太好了.
- Yeah. - Awesome.
你的设计团队在哪里?
Where's your design team?
团队? 我没有团队...
Team? I don't...
让我看看进度吧.
Show me your current build.
呃, 显而易见, 简单易用是最重要的.
Well, obviously ease of use is a big feature here.
我们想做一个很简单的用户界面.
We're trying to develop a simpler interface
主要是给一般用户使用.
that's geared towards the real layman end user.
但使用者界面不容易整合啊. 说实话...
But, we're kind of struggling with the interface, and, to be frank...
我们现在做的结果就是...
The results have been...
- 一坨屎.  - 没错.
- Shit. - Yeah.
用什么零组件?
What's it got under the hood?
典型的配置,
Standard kick ass stuff.
64KB记忆体...
Sixty-four K RAM...
256色荧幕, 摩托罗拉6809处理器.
Two fifty-six bitmap display, Motorola 6809.
我们准备使用68000.
We're gonna run the 68000.
但是, 哥们, 那是"丽莎"的处理器.
But dude, that's Lisa's processor.
没错, 哥们.
That's correct. Dude.
我不关心预算是多少. 给我那个处理器就行.
I don't care what the budget is. Give me their processor.
搞掂.
Done.
嘿, 史蒂夫.
Hey, Steve.
你怎样啊, 伙计?
How are you, man?
克里斯, 很高兴见到你...
Chris, it has been a...
耶.
Yep.
- 你在这个部门做"麦金托什"?  - 是.
- You're working on the Macintosh? - Yeah.
不错
Good.
好, 这下有意思了.
Good, this is gonna be fun.
好, 言归正传.
Okay. Let's go back to what you were saying before.
这是给一般大众用的, 对吧?
This thing is for the everyman. Right?
这就是我们的用户.
That's our end user.
老师也好.
It's the school teacher.
清洁工也好.
It's the garbage man.
小屁孩也好. 还是住在内布拉斯加州的老奶奶也好. 对吧?
It's the kid. It's some grandma out in Nebraska. Right?
我们要把这东西做的非常简单.
So we need to make this thing simple.
就像一个...
It's gotta work like...
家电那么简单.
like an appliance.
嘿, 杰夫.
Hey, Jef.
史蒂夫来了.
Steve Jobs is here.
因为你刚才不在...
Since you weren't around...
刚才我们领导层跟摩托罗拉的人开会呢.
Some of the project leads were having a meeting with Motorola.
你来这里要干什么?
Why exactly are you here?
我来帮忙做好"麦金托什".
I'm here to help build the Macintosh.
我不确定这是否可行.
Ah. I'm not sure that that's practical for us.
我们可不想让这个项目
We're actually trying to avoid this project
也被某人毁掉.
becoming another over bloated disaster.
好吧, 杰夫.
Okay, Jef.
你引起了我的注意.
You got my attention.
好吧, 史蒂夫.
Look, Steve.
项目开始的时候, 你不想帮忙.
You didn't want to be involved back when we started this thing,
我无所谓.
and that was fine by me.
你现在过来也好.
I just wanted you to cut the checks.
只是加入就加入, 别把麦金托什
Be involved, just don't turn Macintosh
当成你复仇的工具.
into a measure of revenge for you.
大家都知道你从"丽莎"项目被赶出来了.
Everyone knows about your fallout with Team Lisa.
相信我, 我们现在做的还不错.
So trust me when I say, we're doing fine.
知道了, 杰夫.
Okay, Jef.
我跟你这么说吧.
Let's get a couple things straight.
我们不做得过且过的事情.
We don't do fine.
我们不安于现状.
And we don't accept things the way that they are,
创新不止, 勇往直前.
and we don't stop innovating.
你现在做出的产品, 毫无新意.
Now, your machine lacks power.
现有的用户界面太小, 需要重新设计.
And your little interface, it needs work.
我来帮忙把它做好.
And I'm here to help with that.
我不是要抢走"麦金托什"项目.
Now, I'm not trying to take Macintosh away from you.
我希望你留在团队里.
I want you on this team.
你要么留下来, 要么立马滚蛋.
But you can either get on board, or you can get the fuck out.
好了, 现在我们还有很多正事要做, 所以赶紧干活.
Okay. Now, we've got a lot of work to do. So, let's get to it.
比尔, 跟我来.
Bill, you come with me.
行, 去干什么?
Okay. Where are we going?
招兵买马.
Recruiting.
靠.
Shit.
- 嗨, 史蒂夫.  - 帮我拿一下.
- Hey, Steve. - Hold these for a second.
- 行. - 谢了.
- Yeah. - Thanks.
怎么了? 怎么回事? 你这是演的哪一出?
What, what's going on? What are you doing?
- 史蒂夫?  - 你现在是"麦金托什麦"团队的人了.
- Steve? - You're on the Macintosh Team now.
什么, 史蒂..."麦金托什"是什么?
What, Ste... What's a Macintosh?
安迪.赫兹菲尔德.
Andy Hertzfeld.
听说你你有两把刷子?
Are you good?
我需要非常厉害的人加入"麦金托什"团队,
I only want good people working on Macintosh,
说实话我不知道你是不是有这个本钱.
and I'm not sure if you're good enough.
你说什么?
Excuse me?
比尔.阿特肯森告诉我, 你有两把刷子.
Bill Atkinson says that you're good.
我? ...对头, 我也这么觉得.
I... Yes. I think I'm pretty good.
你觉得自己富有创造性吗?
Are you creative?
我...我...我还可以吧.
I... I... I think so.
欢迎加入"麦金托什"团队.
Welcome to the Macintosh Team.
小屁孩, 你总是让我给你擦屁股救火.
I'm tired of saving your ass, kid.
你好这一口, 我也没辙.
You love saving my ass.
我需要我自己的工程师队伍.
I want my own engineering team.
想要谁你自己挑.
You can pick them yourself.
还有别给我安排什么
And I am done working under the gun
狗屁的项目截止期限.
of your ridiculous deadline bullshit.
随时给你假期去跟大奶妹约会.
You might as well be asking for a date with her.
我也要这项福利.
I want that, too.
没问题.
Done.
谈正经的, 史蒂夫.
Serious, Steve.
这什么意思, 史蒂夫? 这是什么绩效面试吗?
So what is this, Steve? Some sort of performance review?
你现在的IIE项目如何?
How are things going on the IIE?
进展不错. 真的不错.
Things are great. Really great.
你一定觉得超无聊吧?
You're bored to death, aren't you?
是, 我快无聊死了.
Yes. Yes I am.
你想来"麦金托什"团队和我一起打拼吗?
You want to come work with me on the Mac Team?
你想让我进"麦金托什"团队吧?
You're trying to recruit me for the Mac Team, aren't you?
好, 算我一个.
Okay, I'm in.
你一定有难关想要克服.
You've gotta have a problem that you want to solve.
或者有错误想要纠正.
A wrong that you want to right.
这必须是你的激情所在.
And it's gotta be something that you're passionate about,
否则你就不会有毅力坚持下去.
because otherwise you won't have the perseverance to see it through.
别跟我说什么这产品进度不能更快了.
I don't ever want to hear you tell me that you can't make it faster.
我是说, 上百万的人想买这款产品.
I mean, millions of people are gonna buy this machine.
我们不能仅仅是仅仅盯住竞争对手,
And we can't look at the competition
我们要比竞争对手做的更好.
and say we're gonna do it better.
我们得盯住竞争对手, 同事要做到与众不同.
We have to look at the competition and say we're gonna do it differently.
现在我们有机会做一个革命性的电脑产品.
We have an opportunity to build a revolutionary machine.
你一生会做很多事情
And in your life you only get to do so many things.
此时此刻, 我们把生命花在这件事情上
Right now we've chosen to do this.
那就让我们做到极致
So let's make it great.
很棒.
It's great.
不, 我说错了.
No. It's not.
这超级棒的.
It's insanely great.
如果可能, 还要再增加点内存.
We should try to get more memory into it if we can.
但是还得保证按时完工.
We can still hit the timeline.
来看一眼吧.
Take a look at it.
"麦金托什"这个当初的小东西现在"失去控制"了, 史蒂夫.
This little Macintosh side project has gotten out of hand, Steve.
变得太前卫了.
Way beyond the pale.
"丽萨"就被你搞得定价超过1万美元了.
First you created a $10,000 monstrosity with Lisa,
你已经在这个原本投资不大的项目投入了百万美元.
and now you've poured millions
而这本来是个小部门的.
into what was supposed to be a minor diversion.
你错过了多次送货日期,
You've missed multiple ship dates,
此时IBM正在统治个人电脑领域.
and meanwhile, IBM is just purring along.
史蒂夫...
Steve...
人们不像你想像的那样去用电脑.
People don't use computers the way you think they do.
我们应该怎么去给"麦金托什"做市场推广?
How are we even supposed to market the Macintosh?
我们不用杞人忧天.
We don't.
你给我挑出5个CEO候选人, 你该让我来挑选谁做CEO.
You give me five candidates for CEO. You're gonna let me choose.
我说, 我们就找一个市场营销背景的人来
I say we choose someone with a marketing background
帮助我们销售我们从未卖过的产品.
to help us sell what's never been sold.
现在, 我想自己管理这家公司,
Now, while I would like to run my own company,
麦克说服了我, 大家认为我还没准备好.
Mike has helped me understand that you don't think I'm ready.
没错, 你确实还不行.
Yes, because you're not.
好吧.
Okay.
我要约翰.斯卡利.
I want John Sculley.
约翰.斯卡利?
John Sculley?
百事可乐的总裁.
President of Pepsi Cola.
百事可乐公司很不错的人.
The Pepsi Challenge guy.
他很聪明, 是市场营销的天才.
He's smart, he's a marketing genius
为了成功不择手段.
and he'll do whatever it takes to succeed.
史蒂夫, 斯卡利可不好挖.
Steve, Sculley is a tough get.
他是我们的候选人中最难挖到的.
Maybe the toughest on our list.
你凭什么觉得你能把他挖过来?
What the hell makes you think you can get him?
他凭什么离开百事可乐?
Why would he ever leave Pepsi?
因为糖水卖的再好, 也不能名留青史.
Nobody remembers the world's best soda salesman.
我要找一个我能相信的人.
I need somebody I can trust.
你能做出完美的产品,
You can make a great product.
但是你得让人相信--
But you have to convince people
你卖给人们的东西比实际的还要好.
that what you're selling is greater.
我们销售的不是电脑, 我们销售的是电脑能实现梦想的能力
We're not selling computers. We're selling what they can do
一种让思想变成现实的工具.
with a computer.
一种为思想服务的工具.
A tool for the mind.
女士们和先生们, 这工具
And that, ladies and gentlemen,
才是意义深远啊.
is limitless.
因为人们一直相信
Because people will never stop believing
他们能从某件事情获取更多,
that they could get more out of something,
无论是他们的工作, 婚姻, 金钱,
whether it be their jobs, their marriage, their money,
还是他们的生活.
their lives.
他们想要更多, 你们要把Mac往这个方向打造.
That's what you have to do with the Mac.
这就是对无所不能的电脑的信赖.
It's the belief in the limitless.
没有什么是不可能的.
The impossible.
不管你有什么样的梦想, 你总能实现它.
That no matter what you dream, you can do it.
而Mac电脑就能帮你达到梦想的毕岸.
And Mac will help you get there.
几个月前, 史蒂夫来曼哈顿找我,
A few months ago, when Steve was visiting me in Manhattan,
问了我一个很重要的问题. 他问道:
he asked me a very important question. He said,
"你想一辈子卖糖水吗? "
"Do you want to sell sugar water for the rest of your life,
"还是跟我一起改变世界?"
"or come with me, and change the world?"
嗯,
Well,
于是我加入了苹果公司. 谢谢.
Here I am. Thank you.
现在是1984年.
It is now 1984.
看起来IBM想要统治一切.
It appears IBM wants it all.
Apple是阻止IBM的唯一希望.
Apple is perceived to be the only hope
让IBM望洋兴叹.
to offer IBM a run for its money.
蓝色巨人(指IBM公司)是否将独霸电脑业界?
Will Big Blue dominate the entire computer industry?
不可能!
No!
称霸整个信息时代?
The entire information age?
没门!
No!
乔治.奥威尔的关于1984预言是否会成真?
Was George Orwell right about 1984?
不会!
No!
今天, 我们第一次在此庆祝
Today we celebrate the first
"信息纯粹性管理"的周年纪念日.
glorious anniversary of the Information Purification Directives.
这是历史上第一次,
For the first time in all history,
这是一个纯理想主义的后花园.
a garden of pure ideology,
在此的每个工作者工作称心, 表现完美,
where each worker may bloom,
不受他人打扰.
secure from the pests.
我们的竞争对手公司的员工却牢骚满腹的工作到死.
Our enemies shall talk themselves to death.
这是历史上的第一次.
First time in all history.
我们就是应该.
We shall...
引领潮流.
prevail.
1月24日, Apple将发布"麦金托什"电脑.
On January 24th, Apple Computer will introduce Macintosh
你就明白为什么1984不会成为"1984" (详见乔治.奥威尔小说1984)
and you'll see why 1984 won't be like 1984.
干得好.
Good work.
- 什么反响?  - 我都不敢相信.
- Some response, huh? - I can't believe it.
- 这就像一场革命.  - 是的, 它就是一场革命.
- It's a revolution. - It's a revolution.
苹果电脑真的改变了世界.
The thing's a game changer.
你超越了你自己, 史蒂夫.
You really outdid yourself, Steve.
嘿, 为什么不聊个电话联系一下呢?
Hey. Why don't you give me a call?
- 一起吃晚饭.  - 好啊.
- Grab some dinner or something. - Yeah.
- 行.  - 我喜欢这样.
- Okay. - I'd like that.
- 史蒂夫.  - 亚瑟.
- Steve. - Arthur.
干得好.
Great job up there.
谢谢.
Thank you.
史蒂夫, 我想让你知道: 我们一直都相信你.
Steve, I want you to know that we believe in you.
我知道你懂的.
I hope you know that.
谢谢你, 亚瑟.
Thank you, Arthur.
嘿.
Hey.
他想说什么?
What was that?
什么...
What...
若克. 他刚刚...
Rock. He just...
说什么"我们一直相信你".
Said something, "we believe in you."
怎么回事儿?
What's going on?
嗯, 他指的是"麦金托什"电脑.
It's the Macintosh.
你知道, 这个项目太烧钱了.
You know, we had them run the numbers
尝试了100多种方法, 试了100多次...
100 different ways, 100 times over...
- 但是Mac电脑定价太高了.  - 是的.
- You're marking up the Macintosh. - Yep.
如果我们照"旧"玩下去, 那么从产品发布之日就一直在烧钱.
If we keep it as is, we'll be hemorrhaging money by launch date.
我不管, 你得让顾客买单.
You're gonna price out the consumer.
呃, 我们没法做赔本生意.
Well, we can't take the risk of flattening our profits.
不. 我们没法两全其美.
No. We can't have it both ways.
我是说, 你还坚持使用最贵的硬件吗?
I mean, you insisted on the most expensive hardware.
Mac电脑的原本设计很便宜的.
The Mac was originally much cheaper.
杰夫.热斯肯设计了一款售价1000美元的电脑.
Jef Raskin designed a $1,000 box.
我做了个更好的出来.
I made it great.
如果你还想让公司继续盈利的话...
If you want the company to remain profitable...
这是谁的主意?
Whose idea was this?
大家的主意.
It's a group decision.
这是谁的主意?
Whose idea was this?
我的. 不是麦克的, 也不是董事会的主意. 就是我的主意.
It was mine. Not Michael's, not the Board. It was me.
别这么做, 约翰. IBM才做这种蠢事.
We don't do this, John. IBM does this shit.
- 史蒂夫... - Apple不是这种公司, 我也不是这种人.
- Steve... - Not Apple. Not me.
别把我当作成坏人,
Look, don't make me the villain because
我是在为公司利益着想.
I'm looking out for our company's best interests.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
有些事情必须要改变.
Some things have to change.
你要是还执迷不悟,
If you keep heading down this path,
我也没办法保你.
I will not be able to protect you.
你跟那帮孙子一个德行
They got to you.
那帮孙子?
They?
你从哪里搞来的?
How'd you get this?
昨天到货的. 很明显这是测试版, beta版都不算...
Arrived yesterday. It's pre-beta, obviously, but it's all...
这就是纯抄袭.
It's a blatant rip-off.
给比尔.盖茨打电话.
Get me Bill Gates on the phone.
我跟你明说吧, 比尔.
Let me make this perfectly clear, Bill.
我说完的时候, 你才能看穿这件事.
So that when I'm finished, you can still see through those
你这个整天戴着近视眼镜的假文青, 就是无耻到极点的罪犯.
thick pretentious glasses, you psychopathic, unimaginative criminal.
你偷了我的软件, 我会向法院证明你是怎么抄袭的.
You stole my software, and I can prove it in court.
你赚的每一分钱我都要你吐出来.
And I'm gonna sue you for every cent that you have ever made.
我这辈子都不会放过你.
And I will make it my life's mission to see to it that you never,
永不.
never,
你即使给我9成的分成, 我也不会让你赚到一分钱.
ever make another dollar that I don't first take 90 cents.
我知道大家都跟我一样不爽,
I can only assume that you are all as irate as I am,
但你们都不愿意拉下脸来说狠话.
and you're simply too dumbfounded to speak.
乔布斯说会生产一百万台,
Mr. Jobs promised us a million units.
现在四分之一都不到.
We have yet to reach a quarter of that.
是时候做出改变了.
Something has to change.
搞砸了两个项目, 研发费用超支,
With two failed projects, overextended R&Ds,
还跟微软打官司,
and that Microsoft fiasco,
这个季度我们会亏损, 有史以来头一次.
we're about to experience the first quarterly loss in company history.
IBM过去两年有比我们更好的产品
IBM beat us to market by two years
销售业绩也比我们强.
with a better product and better sales.
Mac连玩具都算不上. 简直就是个笑话.
The Macintosh is not even a toy. It's a joke.
IBM准备要转型,
IBM has now moved on to mini decks.
我们也应该这样.
And so should we.
你的意思是什么, 亚瑟?
What are you getting at, Arthur?
各位, 我想该重新定位,
Gentlemen, I believe it's time to reconsider
个人电脑的前景.
the viability of the personal computer.
史蒂夫, 有什么看法?
Steve, anything to say?
你想让我说什么, 亚瑟?
What would you have me say, Arthur?
是你要提高定价的.
You raised our price.
别把怪到我身上.
Don't put that on me.
问题不在定价上, 史蒂夫. 问题是你的产品.
The problem is not the price, Steve. It's your product.
你把Mac定位太高档了,
You over-hyped the Mac.
让顾客一等再等, 一直在给期待Mac的人画饼充饥.
You told people to wait. You sold the future of the Macintosh.
正因如此, 我们过去两年没有产品可卖.
And as a result we lost two years of sales.
这不是我的错.
It's not my fault.
总有人要来顶罪.
Well, it sure as shit is somebody's fault.
呃, 没有人支持我.
Well, I'm not receiving any support.
你不给我资源,
You're stripping me of my resources,
把大把的钱都投在Apple II上.
and dumping millions into the Apple ll.
你知道我们为什么在Apple II上投入那么多吗?
Do you know why we keep dumping millions into the Apple ll?
因为它很畅销, 我们七成的收入都来自Apple II. 但是Mac呢?
Because it sells. It's 70% of our revenue. How's the Mac doing?
我说的很明白.
I made my opinion perfectly clear.
如果你愿意像IBM一样做东西, 我没辙.
If you want to keep sucking on the tailpipe of IBM, then I can't stop you.
但我不会为某人的脑残的决策背黑锅.
But I will not take the blame for the failures of some court jester.
够了, 这样说不太好吧, 史蒂夫....
All right, this is crazy, Steve...
不, 不, 不. 你说谁呢, 史蒂夫?
No. No, no. To whom are you referring, Steve?
不知道, 亚瑟.
I don't know, Arthur.
你说呢.
You tell me.
约翰, 怎么不说话?
John, you're awfully quiet.
啊, 不好意思.
Yeah. I'm sorry.
我觉得无话可说.
I guess I'm just at a loss for words.
做市场的那个家伙. 百事可乐的营销天才
Head of marketing. Pepsi genius.
现在无话可说了.
Loss for words.
是他的问题, 不是Mac产品的问题.
It's him. Not the Mac.
但是整个过程的代价...
But the cost of that process...
1万美元的价签. 这个价签...
$10,000 price tag. That price tag...
去反对他吧, 不要拿Mac出气.
Goes against him, and not against Mac.
挺讽刺的, 不是吗?
It's ironic, isn't it?
你喜欢听巴布狄伦, 我喜欢披头士.
You chose Dylan, I chose, I chose The Beatles.
披头士现在都过气了.
Seems so backward now.
沃兹.
Woz.
你来这儿干什么?
What are you doing here?
很高兴见到你, 史蒂夫.
Good to see you, too, Steve.
我...我有点忙.
I'm... I'm a little bit busy.
能等会儿再聊吗?
Just, do you mind if we talk later?
耶, 耶, 耶, 就一会儿.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah. This'll only take a minute.
我, 呃...
I, uh...
史蒂夫, 我要走了.
I'm leaving, Steve.
行.
Okay.
不, 不, 史蒂夫.
No. No, Steve.
我要离开Apple公司.
I'm leaving Apple.
永远离开公司. 实际上, 我真的这么做了, 只是...
For good. Actually, I already did. I just...
我只是想该先跟你说一声.
I thought I should come back and tell you first.
为什么
Why?
我们都明白这一天迟早会来. 我也说不清...
We both knew this was coming for some time. I don't even...
我都不记得上次我们聊天是什么时候了.
I don't even remember the last time we talked.
那你想要我怎样?
What do you want from me, then?
不是所有人都像你一样整天有的忙,史蒂夫.
Not everyone has an agenda, Steve.
是啊
Right.
你知道的--我还记得我们年轻的时候,
You know, I can still remember when we were just kids,
在你老爹的车库里.
back in your dad's garage.
我们只是想...
And we just wanted to
为和我们一样的人们,做一些很酷的东西出来, 你记得吗?
create cool toys for people like us. You remember that?
记得
Yeah.
现在对你来说, 你不再在乎那些人.
Now it's not about people anymore for you.
你只在乎产品.
No, it's about the product.
最糟糕的是...
Worst of all, it's...
你更在乎你自己.
It's about yourself.
你只在乎你自己的小宇宙, 史蒂夫.
You're the beginning and end of your own world, Steve.
这太狭隘了. 太伤感了.
And it's so small. So sad.
我觉得这样很孤独吧.
And it's... it's gotta be lonely.
我知道你会说
And I know you're gonna say
产品必须
that the product and the person
满足用户的所有需求.
need to be connected and all that,
但我觉得任何产品都无法达到你的要求.
but it will never be what you think it will.
就是达不到.
It just won't.
至少很长一段时间都做不到.
No, not, not for a long time at least.
我不知道你脑子里在琢磨些什么, 史蒂夫, 但是我知道
I don't know what you think is going on, Steve, but I do.
你很不好过.
And it doesn't end well for you.
其实我不想...
And I'm not...
我不想看你这么难受.
I'm not sticking around to watch.
往事如烟
It's been a journey.
我想说
And for the record,
我热爱我们之前做的一切.
I love what we did.
嘿, 这是约翰斯卡利. 我不在, 请留言.
Hi. You've reached John Sculley. Please leave a message.
嗨, 约翰, 我是史蒂夫.
Hey, John. It's Steve.
呃...
Uh...
我就...
I just...
我们还是好搭档, 约翰, 你和我.
We're still partners, John, you and I.
我们必须同心协力.
We are, we're in this together.
嗯...我...
And I, um...
记得给我回电话啊? 那是最好了. 呃...
You just give me a call back? That'd be great. Um...
嗨, 麦克, 我是史蒂夫.
Hey, Mike. It's Steve.
回个电话好吗?
Would you give me a call back?
拜托你了.
Please?
约翰, 你得夺权.
John, you have to take control now.
你知道股东们已经快受不了吗?
Do you have any idea how close our shareholders are to a panic?
他们暗示你毫无作为?
The implications of your inaction?
忘了你的责任吧, 公司都快完蛋了.
Forget your job, the entire company is at stake here.
大家会一起完蛋.
This could ruin everyone.
我知道, 亚瑟, 但我觉得我们还能挽回.
I know, Arthur, but I still think that we can salvage this.
什么都挽回不了了.
Can't salvage anything.
我怀疑...
I doubt...
史蒂夫.
Steve.
麦克.
Mike.
约翰.
John.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
亚瑟.
Arthur.
你怎么来这么早?
What the hell are you doing here so early?
我也想问你们来这么早干嘛.
I could ask you the same question.
来的正好.
This is good.
史蒂夫, 一起谈谈吧. 请坐.
Steve, why don't you join us this time? Have a seat.
现在?
This time?
史蒂夫, 坐下.
Steve, have a seat.
约翰?
John?
- 亚瑟, 我不想说.  - 你必须得说.
- Arthur, I don't want to. - Yes.
你必须说. 开口吧.
You do. Say it.
把你刚才跟我说过的话重复给他听.
Tell him what you've told me.
我发现我没办法继续工作.
I find it increasingly difficult to do my job
因为前进的路上有很大的阻力.
when the greatest obstacle in my path
我做事时, 暗中总有各种阻力作祟.
casts a looming shadow over everything I try to do.
再说一遍?
What did you say?
史蒂夫...
Steve...
你别跟自己过不去了.
You are your own worst enemy.
也别跟这家公司过不去了.
And this company's.
这...真是难以置信.
This... It's unbelievable.
你以为你自己是什么东西?
Who do you think you are?
我是Apple公司的CEO.
I'm CEO of Apple Computer.
雇用你
Hiring you
是我这辈子做的最后悔的事.
was the worst mistake I have ever made.
史蒂夫, 没必要闹成这样.
Steve, it doesn't have to be this way.
好吧, 这样也好.
Okay. That's done.
董事会不能管理公司.
Boards don't run companies.
应该把公司交给创造产品的人来管理.
The people who create the product run the company.
他同意我们用512KB存储器.
He has the nerve to tell me we should have used the 512.
我说我们要512KB存储器.
We told them that it needed a 512.
我们不能用128KB.
We said not to use the 128.
我们知道128KB存储器根本不够用.
We knew 128 kilobytes wasn't gonna get it done when we built it.
斯卡利今晚会去中国,
Sculley is leaving for China tonight.
要待一星期, 所以我们还有时间.
He's gonna be there for a week, so we got time.
我们得拉拢一些人.
We just gotta recruit.
史蒂夫, 斯卡利会发现的.
Steve, Sculley's gonna find out.
然后会发生什么? 你懂的.
And then what happens, you know?
他现在可是CEO.
He's the CEO of the company now.
那是暂时的.
Well, for now.
公司大多人站在我们这边.
But we have the people who make Apple.
哦, 嘿, 麦克,
Oh, hey, Mike.
我们刚开始聊两句而已.
We're just getting started.
兄弟们, 给我们几秒钟说句话.
Guys, give us a second.
约翰取消了去中国的行程.
John's canceled his trip.
他明天就会召集管理层表决.
He's having an executive staff meeting first thing tomorrow.
所以我不是来参加"革命"的, 我只是来通风报信.
So I didn't come to join your revolution. I came to warn you.
他铁了心
He wants to make absolutely sure
要架空你.
you're nothing more than a figurehead.
不给实权, 不给头衔,
No power, no title.
不给团队.
No team.
我还记得我们第一次见面时候, 你雄心勃勃.
I remember thinking when we first met, um, that you were remarkable.
你想做大事.
You wanted to do something truly great.
那时, 我也一样.
And I did, too.
我现在还一样.
I still do.
大丈夫能屈能伸, 跟斯卡利妥协吧. 算我求你了.
Raise the white flag. Concede to Sculley. I'm begging you.
决不可能.
No.
你赢不了的.
You can't win this one.
你跟谁一伙, 麦克?
Whose side are you on, Mike?
你现在必须站好队.
Because there are sides now.
要嘛跟我一伙, 要嘛做我的敌人.
And you're either with me or you're against me.
站在我这边, 麦克?
Are you with me, Mike?
好吧, 史蒂夫, 我跟你一伙.
Yes, Steve. I'm with you.
那好.
Okay.
好吧.
选约翰.斯卡利的人请举手.
Those in favor of John Sculley.
选史蒂夫.乔布斯的举手.
All in favor of Steve Jobs.
麦克.
Mike.
每个董事会成员都必须表态.
Every Board member's vote must be accounted for.
麦克?
Mike?
斯卡利.
Sculley.
我选斯卡利.
I vote for Sculley.
既然如此...接下来我们怎么做?
So, now what do we do?
Apple股价在过去的几年内一直下跌,
Apple's market value has eroded in the past several years,
这导致了前CEO约翰.斯卡利于1993年下课.
which led to the ousting of former chief John Sculley in 1993.
埃迪.伍拉德, 前杜邦公司CEO,
Ed Woolard, former CEO of DuPont,
加入Apple公司成为董事会主席,
has joined Apple as Chairman of the Board.
Apple新CEO吉尔.阿梅里奥说变革迫在眉睫.
New CEO Gil Amelio says sweeping changes are necessary.
乔布斯的新软件公司-NEXT, 正在...
Jobs' computer software company NEXT, has entered into buyout talks
与他的老东家Apple谈收购的事.
with his former company, Apple Computer.
嘿, 去叫醒Lisa问她想吃早餐吗?
Hey, will you wake up Lisa and see if she wants breakfast?
好.
Yeah.
Lisa?
Lisa? 起来.
Lisa? Come on.
你想睡一整天吗?
Are you gonna sleep all day, huh?
哦, 走开啦.
Oh, go away.
啊? 快起来, 都十点了.
Why? I say all day because it's 10:00.
起来, 我给你做早餐.
Laurene made you breakfast.
我不饿.
I'm not hungry.
喂, 你不能整个寒假就这样睡吧.
Well, you can't sleep all winter break.
我就这么打算的.
Yes, I can.
瑞德! 瑞德!
Reed! Reed!
别糟蹋花园了, 好吗?
Can we not run in the garden? Please?
谢了.
Thank you.
你叫醒Lisa了吗?
Were you able to get Lisa up?
啊, 普通人类有这么多觉要睡吗?
Well, how can a human being sleep that much?
她...我不知道她算不算普通人类.
She... I don't know if she's coming or not.
我一会要去农贸市场, 买点东西什么的.
I'm going to the farmer's market today. Just gonna get a few things.
你今天有计划吗? 要不要一起去?
You have any plans? You want to come with me?
什么?
Hmm?
我问你今天有什么安排?
I said do you have plans?
今天?
Today?
喂, 吉尔.阿梅里奥(Apple当时的CEO)会过来谈谈.
Well, Gil Amelio is gonna stop by.
交接一些关于软件的事情.
They're transitioning in some of our software.
行啊.
Okay.
我...我就是帮忙而已. 他们需要一点帮助.
I'm... I'm just helping them out. They just need a little help.
哦, 伙计.
Oh, boy.
我不爽了, 不是吗?
I'm in trouble, aren't I?
史蒂夫, 我怎样做你才愿意回来?
Steve, what can I do to convince you to come back?
你想怎么说服我
What can you do to convince me
我不需要坐上"泰坦尼克"号那样的高规格待遇的, 吉尔?
I wouldn't be boarding the Titanic, Gil?
因为我知道你深爱Apple, 而NEXT公司只是你暂时落脚的地方.
Because I know how you feel about Apple. What NEXT could never be.
再说, 想想你现在拥有...
Plus, you know, considering that you now own
150万份Apple公司的股票.
a million and a half shares of Apple,
我是大伙, 这可是一大笔投资.
I mean, that's a tangible investment, too.
你们这帮家伙一定快绝望了.
You guys must be pretty desperate.
才没有呢.
We're not desperate.
Newton项目怎么样了?
How are things going with the Newton?
那是前任的蠢主意.
Look, don't blame me for the failures of the last regime.
那个项目不能再烂了.
It's not as bad as you think.
你也看到了, 裁员了不少人,
You're overseeing massive layoffs.
Apple的股价又创新低了.
Apple stock just set another record low.
你们4个月后就要破产清算了, 吉尔.
And you're four months from insolvency, Gil.
我说, 你们业绩这么差...
I'd say that's pretty bad.
耶, 为了保证公司还能运转下去
Well, yeah. In order to fix what's broken,
我们得做出一些牺牲, 对吧?
some sacrifices are necessary. All right?
史蒂夫, 你到底怎么才肯回来?
Steve, what do you need?
任何条件我都答应.
Name it.
- 史蒂夫.  - 吉尔.
- Steve. - Gil.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
麦克.
Mike.
很高兴见到你.
It's nice to see you.
来, 带你参观一下.
Come on, I'll show you around.
不, 吉尔, 不用担心. 我带他逛一圈.
No, Gil, don't worry about it. I'll give him the tour.
你确定?
You sure?
耶, 必须的, 绝对没问题. 放马过来.
Yeah, sure. No problem. Come on.
那就好.
That's great.
去吧, 你们好好逛. 我...
You guys go ahead. I'll...
我一会就去找你们.
I'll catch up.
史蒂夫, 有些事得跟你说清楚.
There's something I always wanted you to know, Steve.
当初赶你走, 不是我的决定.
It was never my call.
别提跑哪破事儿了, 麦克.
Let's not do this, Mike.
不, 这事很重要. 你知道的, 当时我努力了.
No, this is important. You know, I tried.
我挺你的的. 我一直是这样做的.
I wanted you here. I always did.
我费了好长时间才把你弄回来.
It's too bad it took me so long to get you back.
不, 我还没回来啊.
Oh, I'm not back.
耶, 你会回来的.
Yeah. You will be.
我们拭目以待吧.
We'll see about that.
好了, 我自己逛逛就好.
You know, I'm gonna show myself around.
我从这儿开始.
I'll take it from here.
贱人一个.
Son of a bitch.
这谁设计的?
Who did these?
是我, 先生.
I did, sir.
你叫什么?
Who are you?
强纳生.伊夫. 我是工业设计主管.
Jonathan Ive. I'm Director of Industrial Design.
你怎么还在这里?
Why are you still here?
现在是周一上午11点(上班时间)啊.
It's 11:00 a.m. on a Monday.
不.
No.
我问你为什么还待在Apple公司?
Why are you still here at Apple?
我创立的Apple公司不是这样的.
This isn't the company I built.
没品位, 没格调.
There's no taste, no style.
没什么设计可言.
No design.
除非有什么让你驻足不前, 你为什么要留在这样的地方?
So unless they're shackling you here, why do you stay?
哎, 先生, 我想其实还有一群人,
Well, sir, I guess I would say there are still
始终相信Apple的理念.
those of us that believe in what Apple stood for.
你所倡导的理念.
What you stood for.
你觉得我倡导什么理念?
What do you think I stood for?
我觉得...
I think...
我觉得, 你相信Apple的使命, 是让电脑,
I think you believe that the computer,
随身听或者类似设备
or the Walkman, or whatever it may be,
成为个人生活的自然延伸.
should be a natural extension of the individual.
正是这种使命,
And it's that mission,
这种追求完美质量, 还有创新点子和心灵感动的激情...
that devotion to quality, and ideals, and heart...
就是我们留在这里的原因. 也许我们还有机会东山再起.
That's what keeps us here. That we might do it once more.
好. 甭管你现在在做什么,
Okay. Whatever you're working on,
你们要把现在这些设计全都忘掉.
the rest of the day I want you to forget it.
我要每个人重新开始, 设计点新东西出来.
I want everyone to design something new.
我不在乎它是什么, 是不是高科技产品,
I don't care what it is, I don't care if it's technology,
就尽管去创造吧.
just create something.
做些更有用的东西.
Something useful.
做些你真正在乎的东西.
Something you care about.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
你回来了我们真高兴.
We're glad you're back.
我还没真的回来呢.
I'm not back.
暂时没有.
Yet.
史蒂夫.
Steve.
啊!
Ugh!
垃圾货.
Junk.
史蒂夫, 这是我们的董事会主席埃迪.伍拉德.
Steve, you met our Chairman, Ed Woolard.
- 史蒂夫 - 你好.
- Steve. - Hi.
听着, 呃...
Look, um...
我知道你之前被坑的很惨.
I know all about the bad blood you must taste.
知道你不会轻易地相信我.
And I understand your hesitation to trust me.
我只想说
But I just want you to know
我跟之前那位主席亚瑟.若克不一样. 我是你的朋友.
I am not Arthur Rock. I'm your friend.
好啊.
Okay.
因此, 我们能聊两句吗?
So, can we take a minute to talk?
好啊.
Apparently.
今天的报纸.
Today's paper.
我相信你看了新闻了.
I'm sure you've seen the news.
对不起, 埃迪, 你具体一点最好.
I'm sorry, Ed, you're gonna have to be more specific.
一夜之间, 我们的股价大跌7.5%.
Our shares dropped 7.5% overnight.
跌到十年来的最低点.
It's the lowest it's been in 10 years.
上周有个匿名投资者
Last week an unidentified investor
狂抛了150万股.
dropped one point five million shares.
股民都恐慌了, 史蒂夫.
Put a real scare into the marketplace, Steve.
150万股这么多啊? 哈.
One point five million shares? Wow.
我想, 我们的股民都吓疯了吧.
I guess the stockholders must be getting restless.
我们想让你回来, 史蒂夫.
We want you here, Steve.
我已经回来了, 是你们的顾问了.
I'm here. As a consultant.
我们想让你重回CEO宝座
As CEO.
- CEO?  - 没错.
- CEO? - Yeah.
起码先试用一阵子.
At least in the interim.
那吉尔呢?
And Gil?
啊, 他? 吉尔快要下台了.
Yeah, well, Gil's halfway out the door.
他也知道自己不行,
He has to see the writing on the wall.
他就是爱面子还在死撑.
At least if he's not too proud to admit it.
哦, 他(麦克)会想办法把吉尔搞走, 找个机会让你出山.
Oh, he's going to try to force you out, and make a case against you.
我以前在哪儿见过这种手段(指之前把史蒂夫挤出Apple的事情)?
Where have I seen this before?
吉尔有潜在危险, 他没有筹码了, 很快就会走人.
Gil's on the ledge. He doesn't have a play here.
我们只需要你一点稍微肯定的答复.
All we need is a little push from you.
如果你想夺回失去的公司, 现在正是天赐良机.
If you want to get back what you lost, this is the time.
我没有失去它, 它是被偷走的.
I never lost it. It was stolen from me.
电脑一点都不性感, 没有曲线美.
There's no sex left in computers. No curves.
如果说电脑是艺术和美结合的产物,
Now, if computers are for art, and beauty,
并用来连接全球的每个人, 为什么现在的电脑都这么丑?
and global interconnectivity, why are they so ugly?
你知道的, 电脑应该是有艺术感的, 但是没有人在意这些.
You know, it should be artful. But no one cares.
人们对电脑的印象都是非黑即白那么刻板,
The world may mistakenly see computers only in black and white,
但是, 我们的生活, 我们的梦想, 我们的颜色, 都是五彩缤纷的.
but we live, and we dream and we paint in color.
电脑也应该是这样.
And we think the computer should, too.
你觉得怎么样?
What do you think?
强尼, 你一定要对我开诚布公.
Jony, I always want you to be honest with me.
不论发生什么,
No matter what.
一定要对我实话实说.
Just be brutally honest.
明白吗?
Understand?
我明白.
Understand.
你自己觉得呢?
What do you think?
我觉得, 这个蓝色,
I think, I think the blue,
不是很满意.
it's not quite right.
这有个傻主意. 把音响内建到机器里面怎么样?
Here's a dopey idea. What if we put the speakers inside?
别逗了, 史蒂夫, 吉尔和董事会
Yeah, Steve, Gil Amelio and the board
不可能批准. 没门.
are not gonna allow that. No way.
我们才不管他们批不批准,
We're not gonna ask for permission.
史蒂夫帮了我很多忙
Steve's done an admirable job assisting me
尤其在他当顾问这段时间.
as an advisor during this, this period.
他的执行力和创造力没得说.
And while I commend his actions, and his initiatives,
我相信, 现在是时候做进一步的调整.
I believe it's now in our best interest to move on,
今天起, 史蒂夫将不再担任顾问一职.
and relieve Steve of his advisory role in this company.
我同意, 吉尔.
I agree, Gil.
是吗
You do?
是, 我也认为史蒂夫不应该继续留在现在的职位
I do think it's time Steve step out of his current role, yes.
史蒂夫?
Steve?
谢谢你, 埃迪.
Thank you, Ed.
我想跟董事会分享一下, 我对Apple未来的规划.
I'd like to present the Board my vision for the future of Apple.
我们不是微软或者戴尔.
We're not Microsoft or Dell.
所以, 不要再学他们了.
So we need to stop trying to be that.
我们需要回头看看我们的根本, 我们的强项.
We need to go back to who we are, and what we do best,
其他的抛开不要管.
and throw away everything else.
我们擅长做电脑,
Here's how we're gonna do it.
我们要建立新的电脑产品线
We're gonna build a new line of computers
家用和商用都要兼顾
for the home, and for the office.
我们要以NEXT为基础, 做一个全新的操作系统.
We're gonna build a new operating system on the backbone of NEXT.
这就是下一代的"麦金托什".
The next generation of Macintosh.
我们打算砍掉所有其他的项目,
And we're gonna kill every other project.
全部砍掉.
Everything.
这个公司, 决不能再出现屎一样的产品.
This company will not make shit anymore.
我们要扩大广告预算.
We're also gonna double down on the advertising budget.
Charite 是我们唯一的御用广告公司.
Chiat Day will be the only advertising agency we use.
就像过去一样.
Just like back in the old days.
简而言之,
In short,
我们打算把Apple做得跟以前一样酷.
we're gonna make Apple cool again.
当然, 我可能没法重振Apple
But I will not be able to move forward
如果董事会的全体成员不给我运营自主权的话.
without the Board's permission to operate under complete autonomy.
我要成为董事会的全权投票成员. 最后一点是...
I'll be made a full voting member of the Board. And lastly...
临时CEO.
Interim CEO.
嘿, 等等.
Now, hold on.
我才是CEO, 你们这是...
I'm the CEO, and this is...
听着, 是你们逼我到这个地步的.
Look, you put me in this position.
Apple公司就像一条破船, 底部有洞, 正在漏水,
Apple is like a ship with a hole in the bottom, and it's leaking water.
而我是船长, 我的工作就是负责...
And it's my job to make sure that
把船带往正确的方向.
we point the ship in the right direction.
你们为什么不让我继续干呢?
So why don't you let me do my job?
好吧, 我们还是来投票表决吧.
All right, let's put this to a vote.
谁同意史蒂夫来掌权?
Those in favor?
你们搞什么鬼?
What the hell?
埃迪?
Ed?
麦克?
Mike?
不好意思, 吉尔. 对事不对人.
Sorry, Gil. Nothing personal.
你在成长过程中, 会有人告诉你,
When you grow up, you tend to get told
世事如棋, 但江湖险恶.
the world is the way that it is,
你的生活就是在社会上混日子
your life is just to live your life inside the world
不要太执着, 不撞南墙不回头.
and try not to bash into the walls too much.
但是生命有限.
But that's a very limited life.
生活的道路可以变得很宽广,
Life can be much broader,
你只需要明白一点, 就是...
once you discover one simple fact.
围绕你的一切
And that is that everything around you
即所谓的现实生活
that you call life
都是一群比你蠢的人为了愚弄你而编造出来的东西.
was made up by people that are no smarter than you.
你可以改变它, 影响它.
And you can change it. You can influence it.
你可以走你自己的路, 让别人去跟风.
You can build your own things, that other people can use.
别管那些错误连篇的胡扯, 例如:
It's to shake off this erroneous notion
什么"生活就在那里, 不离不弃",
that life is just there,
什么"活在当下", 什么"不能反抗, 就享受生活"之类的.
and you're just gonna live in it, versus embrace it.
你应该改变生活, 改善生活, 让自己的生活与众不同.
Change it. Improve it. Make your mark upon it.
只要你学会了这点, 你就不会成为凡夫俗子.
And once you learn that, you'll never be the same again.
但是我们的现金流状况...
But in our cash position...
CEO先生.
Mr. CEO.
麦克.
Mike.
你找我吗?
You wanted to talk to me?
欢迎. 请坐吧.
Welcome. Please. Have a seat.
- 埃迪.  - 嘿, 戈热斯.
- Ed. - Hey, Gareth.
麦克.
Mike.
这是什么?
What's this?
一个机会.
It's an opportunity.
我很久没见到伯纳德(Apple的法律顾问)了.
I haven't seen Bernard around for a few days.
凯瑟琳和德拉诺去哪儿了?
Where's Katherine, Delano?
刘易斯先生和哈德逊夫人(即:德拉诺和凯瑟琳, Apple的两位董事会成员), 做了艰难而轻松的决定:
Mr. Lewis and Mrs. Hudson made a difficult decision easier
很通情达理地退出董事会了.
by agreeing to step down from the Board.
真的吗?
Really?
他俩都接受了一笔可观的高管遣散费("金保护伞"费).
They both agreed to accept incredibly generous golden parachutes.
同样的机会给你, 细节在信封里面.
The same opportunity is detailed inside that envelope.
所以你要把我们赶走?
So you're forcing us out?
我这么做事出有因.
With good reason.
什么原因?
And what's that?
当前的形势对公司的发展是
The current arrangement is
不利的.
inhibiting.
我没办法拖着累赘前进, 麦克.
I can't hold everyone's hand while we cross the street, Mike.
所以你的下一步举措就是直接干掉董事会?
And so your next big move is to eradicate your Board?
你觉得这可行吗?
And you think you can just do that?
不好意思, 麦克. 是时候这样做了.
I'm sorry, Mike. But it's time.
拿着这笔高管遣散费吧, 这回报绝对赚到了.
Take the parachute. It's more than fair.
20年了
Twenty years.
你知道吗, 我告诉过我自己: 我在这儿...
You know, I told myself I'd be out of here
顶多干到30多岁就会退出.
while I was still in my thirties.
现在你看看我, 我真的是老了.
And now look at me. I'm practically an old man.
先生们.
Gentlemen.
谢谢, 麦克.
Thanks, Mike.
好...
So...
接下来我们干什么?
What are we gonna do now?
我们将让世界震撼.
We're gonna put a dent in the universe.
致疯狂的人们,
Here's to the crazy ones.
特立独行者,
The misfits,
叛逆的家伙们,
the rebels,
捣蛋鬼们,
the troublemakers,
方孔里的圆头钉子们(不适应社会的人),
the round pegs in the square holes,
那些想法与众不同的人们,
the ones who see things differently.
他们是那些痛恨条条框框的人,
They're not fond of rules,
他们是对现状不满的人,
and they have no respect for the status quo.
你可能认同他们,
You can quote them,
讨厌他们,
disagree with them,
赞美他们或者诋毁他们,
glorify or vilify them.
你唯一无法做到的,
About the only thing you can't do
就是对他们视而不见,
is ignore them.
因为他们改变了世界,
Because they change things.
他们推动了人类进步.
They push the human race forward.
有些人可能认为他们是一群疯子,
And while some may see them as the crazy ones,
但我们认为他们是天才.
we see genius.
因为这群人足够疯狂
Because the people who are crazy enough
勇于去想像他们能改变世界
to think they can change the world
也正是他们改变着世界.
are the ones who do.
录的如何?
How was that?
2012年9月, Apple成为全球市值最高的公司.
Apple became the most valuable company in the market in September, 2012.